<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The summe of all, (namely) Gods service, and mans salvation And a briefe of mans dutie to God concerning both: which is, seeking to serve God while hee lives, and to be saved, when hee dyes. By William Chibald, rector of S. Nic. Col. Abby in Old Fishstreete.</title>
            <author>Chibald, William, 1575-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 186 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 152 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116462</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851678</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851678</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16967</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18605)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16967)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1302:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The summe of all, (namely) Gods service, and mans salvation And a briefe of mans dutie to God concerning both: which is, seeking to serve God while hee lives, and to be saved, when hee dyes. By William Chibald, rector of S. Nic. Col. Abby in Old Fishstreete.</title>
                  <author>Chibald, William, 1575-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 274, [10] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Haviland?] for Robert Bostocke, at the signe of the Kings head in Paules Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two dialogues.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:16967:1"/>
            <head>THE APPROBATION.</head>
            <p>Libellum hunc, à viro Anglo, docto &amp; pio, perlegendum curauimus; eiuſque iudicio probatum, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum duximus.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>25. Ianuarij.</hi> 1599.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Matthias Archiepu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Mechlinienſis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16967:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SVMME OF ALL, <hi>(namely)</hi> GODS ſervice, and Mans ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And A Briefe of Mans dutie to God concerning both:</hi> Which is, ſeeking <hi>To ſerve God while hee lives,</hi> And <hi>To be ſaved, when hee dyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By WILLIAM CHIBALD, Rector of S. <hi>Nic. Col. Abby</hi> in Old Fiſhſtreete.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Boſtocke,</hi> at the Signe of the Kings head in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aules Churchyard. 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16967:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16967:2"/>
            <head>TO MY DEARELY beloved Neighbours, <hi>the Inhabitants of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> of S. <hi>Nic. Col. Abby</hi> in Old Fiſhſtreet, LONDON.</head>
            <p>ALL divine truths and duties are therefore worthy to be knowne, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by men, becauſe they have beene worthy to bee revealed, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by God: But of them all, the heavenly truthes of Gods ſervice, and Mans ſalvation; &amp; the holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſeeking after both, are most worthy of their
<pb facs="tcp:16967:3"/>knowledge and practiſe.</p>
            <p>For if thoſe things be chiefly to be ſought after, that are beſt wo thy of our ſeeking: If thoſe things be best worthy of our ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, that doe moſt neerely concerne us. And if Gods ſervice and Mans ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation doe moſt neerely concerne us; becauſe the one most neerely concernes our dutie to God, and the other our happineſse from God: then ought Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians chiefly to ſeeke after Gods ſervice, and their owne ſalvation.</p>
            <p>The rather: Partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all other Divinitie doth but ſerve to further
<pb facs="tcp:16967:3"/>Chriſtians in ſeeking after theſe two: and partly alſo, becauſe all other without theſe, will never make them wiſe with that wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<note place="margin">Pſal: 111.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 2 Tim: 3 15.</note> 
               <hi>The beginning whereof is Gods feare,</hi> and the end their owne <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon theſe and the like grounds, (my dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved people and Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners) I have endeavoured to instruct you in theſe two points, and what I have taught you concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them in my Sermons, I have now put into a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle booke, with ſome addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; to the end, your eyes by reading, as well as
<pb facs="tcp:16967:4"/>your eares by preaching, may witneſſe how unfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly <hi>I deſire</hi> you ſhould ſerve God,
<note place="margin">Rom: 10.1.</note> and he <hi>ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The booke is but little, (it is the fitter to be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in your pockets, &amp; kept in your memories.) And it is framed in a Dialogue, or familiar conference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt my ſelfe and one of you, hoping to drawe you, better to like of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter therein contained, by my friendlie manner of handling it.</p>
            <p>Though the Dialogue and conference be betwixt but one of you and my ſelfe: yet is it in the name and for the benefit of you
<pb facs="tcp:16967:4"/>all; upon whom it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed for a <hi>New-yeares gift</hi> by him, who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed himſelfe upon you theſe many yeares,
<note place="margin">2 Cor: 12.15.</note> &amp; who will yet hee <hi>ſpent upon you</hi> (to Gods pleaſure) for the furthering of you in the ſervice of God unto your ſalvation.</p>
            <p>What remaines, but that as I have made my labors yours, by publiſhing them for you, and dedicating them unto you; ſo you would endeavour to make them your owne, by peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them, and labouring to benefit your ſelves and families, by reading them together, by conference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb facs="tcp:16967:5"/>them, and prayer to God for his bleſsing upon them to your edification.</p>
            <p>I have heretofore made and publiſhed other bookes (beſides this) for your learning: but how you have uſed and peruſed them to this end, is better known to God, your ſelves and Houſholds, than unto me. If you have endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to build up your ſelves in grace by them, I ſhall be glad to ſee the fruites thereof: But if you have only contented your ſelves with this, that they were made for you, given unto you, and that you have them lying on your ſhelves
<pb facs="tcp:16967:5"/>or in your cheſts, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce to heare of your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment in uſing this booke better;
<note place="margin">Ioſ. 14.15.</note> if now <hi>you and your houſhold</hi> will ſeeke to <hi>ſerve the Lord,</hi> and to be ſaved.</p>
            <p>You ſhall doe this the better, if you will obſerve theſe Directions.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> I would have you to reade it often, becauſe the ſubject matter of it, is of ſuch neceſſary, ordinary, and excellent uſe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> I would have you (as you reade it) to examine &amp; conſider, how you have knowne the truthes, and practiſed the duties taught therein, concerning Gods
<pb facs="tcp:16967:6"/>ſervice, and mans ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ſo you may ſee cauſe, either to repent of your ignorance, and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence herein for time paſt; or to grow in your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and diligence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe points in time to come.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I would have you to call to minde, and uſe, the ſeverall duties that are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to Gods Attributes of greatneſſe, or goodneſſe, or to Gods workes of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or justice, as by Gods providence they ſhall come into your thoughts, or fall out in the world: and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that (before you goe to any holy Ordinance of
<pb facs="tcp:16967:6"/>God, appointed for his publike ſervice) you would looke into this booke for the particular duties which belong unto them ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; to the end you may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe your ſelves to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme thoſe Ordinances, with thoſe duties accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. The like direction I give for the reading o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my booke of the Lords Supper, before you goe to the Communion. And this is the greateſt recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence that I will require of you for my love, and it is the least requitall you can make me for my labour.
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 30.18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The good Lord</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and encourage <hi>every
<pb facs="tcp:16967:7"/>one</hi> of you, to <hi>ſet your hearts to ſeeke God, the Lord God of your fathers,</hi> (that is) to ſeeke to ſerve God, while you live on earth; that when you dye, you may be ſaved in heaven by Ieſus Chriſt: in whom I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours all, and all yours WILLIAM CHIBALD</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16967:7"/>
            <head>SEEKING to ſerve God, while we live</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pariſhioner.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVIth your leave Sir; if I ſhould not be too troubleſome to you, I would faine ſpeake a word with you in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>You are welcome, I pray you come in, and ſit downe, good neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:16967:8"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, I humbly thank you for your kindneſſe, and pray you to pardon my boldneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>You are not ſo bolde as welcome: I pray you be covered, and tell mee what is your will with me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, I haue lived in your pariſh, vnder your publike Miniſtery a good while, and yet I remaine very ignorant; therefore am I come vnto you, for ſome private inſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And I am as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to inſtruct you, as you are to learne; if you come not (as many doe) to aske curious queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16967:8"/>which tend not to godly edification; but contention, and vaine glory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Surely Sir, (if I may be beleeved) my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming is to no ſuch end; but to learne ſuch things, as are moſt chiefly and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily to be learned.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Your intent is good, and I am as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to inſtruct you, as you are to be inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but tell mee your mind yet more plainly, and fully,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will Sir, &amp; it is this by your favour; The whole Bible is large, it containes many bookes, chapters, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16967:9"/>verſes, and in each of them are comprehended many divine truthes: All theſe are worthy of my lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, if I had either time or wit to attaine the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of them: but of theſe many, ſome (me thinkes) ſhould bee more needfull to be learned than others, are they not I pray you?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, that they bee: for though you muſt not neglect the knowledge of any truth revealed by God in the holy Scriptures; yet muſt you chiefly ſecke to know ſome things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove others.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16967:9"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And I pray you (Sir) may not theſe chiefe points be drawne to ſome generall heads for the help of my memory, which is but weake?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Yea. There be two generall heads of them: whereof the firſt is, to ſeek to ſerve God while you live; and the ſecond is, to ſeeke to be ſaved when you die.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>God forbid but we ſhould all ſeeke after both theſe things. But I pray you (good Sir) first declare the first point vnto me at this time, and then handle the ſecond at ſome other opportunity: for I would be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16967:10"/>loth to hold you too long at once.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I will. For the handling then of the 1. point, which is this; <hi>You must ſeeke to ſerve God while you live:</hi> you muſt obſerve that there be 3. branches of it, and that are contained in it. 1. <hi>That you must ſerve God.</hi> 2. <hi>That you must ſeek to ſerve God.</hi> 3. <hi>That you must ſeek to ſerve God while you live.</hi> Of the firſt I ſhall haue juſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſpeake, when I come to treate, how you may bee affected with the ſervice of God; for there I ſhall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16967:10"/>ſpeake of the neceſſitie of Gods ſervice, and that it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded vs by God, and therefore we muſt ſerve God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I pray you then, good Sir, follow your owwe minde and order: let that point alone till then, and now goe on to ſhew me the ſecond branch, which is, that</hi> I muſt ſeek to ſerve God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I will: and in the handling of this I would haue you to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe 5. particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. 1. That wee muſt ſeeke to ſerve God. 2. Why we muſt ſeeke to ſerve God. 3. How,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16967:11"/>and in what manner. 4. In what meaſure. 5. What are the markes of them, that ſeeke to ſerve God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I pray you prove vnto me, that I muſt ſeeke to ſerve God, for I would faine binde my looſe heart to obedience.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It is proved by many places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſpecially theſe, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9. wherein <hi>David</hi> in the name of the Lord, exhorts and commands <hi>Salomon,</hi> and all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to ſeeke to ſerve God: So did <hi>Aſa</hi> the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14.4.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:16967:11"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now I pray you ſhew me why I must ſeeke to ſerve God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The reaſons why are theſe. 1. You muſt encourage others to ſeeke to ſerve God, <hi>Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</hi> 4.2. therefore you muſt much more doe it your ſelfe. 2. You have many examples hereof in the Scriptures, which are patternes for you to follow, as the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14.7. &amp; 15.15. <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.9. <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 119.45. and many other. 3. The benefits of ſeeking to ſerve God ſhould move you herunto, which are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16967:12"/>that God will <hi>reward the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Heb.</hi> 11.6. that <hi>Gods hand ſhall bee vpon them for good, Ezra.</hi> 8.20. that they ſhall <hi>find God,</hi> (namely) to be gracious to them; 1 <hi>Chron,</hi> 28.9. and that <hi>they ſhall not be confounded,</hi> (that is) of their ſinnes or afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 96.6. 4. You ought to bee moved herunto, by the danger of not ſeeking God to ſerve him; which dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger appeares: 1. in that it is a ſigne and marke of a man in his naturall eſtate, &amp; without grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.11. and 2. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch as ſeeke him
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16967:12"/>not, are lyable to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments temporall, that they <hi>ſhall not proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Ier.</hi> 10.21. but <hi>be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, Zeph.</hi> 1.3.4.6: and alſo eternall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Gods power and wrath is againſt them. Ezra.</hi> 8.20.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shew me (I pray you) now, how I muſt ſeeke to ſerve God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The manner how you muſt ſeeke to ſerve God is this. 1. You muſt <hi>prepare</hi> your heart to it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.18. 2. You muſt doe it <hi>joyfully,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.15. 3. You muſt ſeeke to ſerve God <hi>ſincerely,</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:16967:13"/>1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 24.14.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tell me alſo (I pray you) in what meaſure I muſt ſeeke to ſerve God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The meaſure is, 1. <hi>Betimes,</hi> not putting it off to old age, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 34.3. <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.21. 2. <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ligently, Hebr.</hi> 11.6. 3. Earneſtly, <hi>with all our ſoules, Deut.</hi> 4.29. <hi>Ier.</hi> 29.13. 4. <hi>Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, Pſal.</hi> 16.11.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the marks of them that ſeeke to ſerve God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are theſe. 1. They haue <hi>pure hearts and hands,</hi> (that is) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and actions,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16967:13"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.4.6. 2. They deſire to know Gods wayes, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 58.2. and they ſhall know (and <hi>vnderſtand all things, Prov.</hi> 28.5.) 3. They <hi>call vpon God,</hi> and are frequent in prayer, <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.21. <hi>Ier.</hi> 29.12, 13. <hi>Iſay.</hi> 55.5. 4. They <hi>forſake their wicked wayes Hoſ.</hi> 7.10. <hi>Iſay.</hi> 55.5, 6.5. They <hi>feare</hi> to offend God, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3.5. 6. They <hi>delight in God, Mal.</hi> 3.1. 7. They <hi>waite vpon God</hi> by faith, and ſtay his leiſure for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing of his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.25. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.6.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:16967:14"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But why must wee ſeeke to ſerve God whilest we live here?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe, this preſent life is the time of doing ſervice to <hi>God, Luk.</hi> 1.74, 75. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12. and the life to come is the time of receiving our reward from God (in his free favour) for our faithfull ſervice done vnto him here: <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.23, 34.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, I thanke you; for theſe are good reaſons indeed; for they ſhew both that we muſt ſeeke to ſerve God, and why wee must, and other excellent points; but I would alſo faine
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16967:14"/>know, By what meanes I may ſeeke to ſerve God here in this world?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>That is to bee learned alſo; and the meanes are threefold: 1. by ſeeking to know what Gods ſervice is: 2. by ſeeking to deſire and affect Gods ſervice: 3. by ſeeking to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and practiſe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I pray you (Sir) what is the ſervice of God, and wherein doth it conſiſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Serving God, is obeying his will, and doing what he bids vs, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.16. for to ſerve an ordinary Maſter is, to obey his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16967:15"/>will, and to doe as hee would have vs: <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.5.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein is Gods will obeyed for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice? and what things must they doe to that end?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>That Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans may ſerve God, and obey his will, they muſt doe divers duties; and theſe duties have reſpect, either, 1. to God, or, 2. to our neighbour, or, 3. to our ſelves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are of 2. kindes, for they have reſpect vnto God, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16967:15"/>1. immediately, as he is in himſelfe, and in reſpect of ſome things in him; or 2. mediately by the meanes, and in reſpect of ſome things, that proceed, and come from him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne God immediately as he is in himſelfe?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Duties to God in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of himſelfe immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are either 1. generall, or 2. ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall duties?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p n="1">1. Knowledge and beleefe, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9. <hi>Pſal,</hi> 100.2, 3. 1. that there is a God, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.6. 2. that there is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16967:16"/>but one God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.6. 3. that in the Godhead there be three glorious perſons, namely, the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Sonne,</hi> and the <hi>holy Ghost,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.7. 4. that the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is this <hi>God, Deut.</hi> 5.6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The having of a God, and the taking, chooſing, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> onely for our God: <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.3. <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 24.22.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what are the ſpeciall duties which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne GOD immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They be ſuch
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16967:16"/>as concerne his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, being, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is God in his Nature?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>God is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, infinite in all perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.24. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Certaine divine Attributes, whereby (as it were) a part of his divine nature, or ſome holy quality of God, is ſhadowed out vnto vs; and they are of two kindes, for they beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken either 1. his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16967:17"/>or 2. his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes of God,
<note place="margin">Gods At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes of Greatneſſe.</note> which ſet forth his Greatneſſe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, whereby he is able to worke, and doe, what hee knowes is to bee done, and what he wills ſhall be done; and they are theſe ſixe: 1. Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleneſſe, or abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, 2. Infiniteneſſe; 3. Eternity; 4. Immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity; 5. Wiſedome; 6. Almightineſſe, or All-ſufficiency.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluteneſſe, or Simpleneſſe of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:16967:17"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Simpleneſſe is a faculty in God, which removeth from him all compoſition of parts, (as ſoule and body, &amp;c) and whereby he is God of himſelfe, and every thing in God, is God himſelfe: <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.14. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.16.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niteneſſe of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Infiniteneſſe is a faculty in God, which denieth vnto him all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation, and whereby the perfections that are in God are in him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all meaſure: <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 11.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.5.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:16967:18"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Eternity is a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie in God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is vncapable, of beginning, ſucceſſion, or ending: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.2.4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the Immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Immenſity is a faculty in God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is every where, and cannot be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in any one place 1 <hi>Kings.</hi> 8.27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.7.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Wiſedome is a faculty in God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he perfectly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe, and in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16967:18"/>himſelfe all things, that have any kinde of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Iob</hi> 9.3, 4. <hi>Acts.</hi> 15.18.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the All-mightineſſe, or All-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Almightineſſe is a faculty in God, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee is All-ſufficient to doe whatſoever hee can will: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 135.6. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Sir, I humbly confeſſe to Gods glory, and mine owne ſhame, that I was ignorant of most of theſe points, and I bleſſe God for the knowledge of them thus farre by your meanes; but proceede (I
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16967:19"/>pray you) to teach me alſo what are the Attributes of God, which betoken his Goodneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I will,
<note place="margin">Gods At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes of Goodneſſe</note> Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor; &amp; they are vertues, whereby hee is willing and ready, to doe and worke well: and they are theſe foure. 1. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, 2. Mercy, 3. Iuſtice, 4. Love.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Holineſſe is a vertue in God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee is pure from all evill and ſinne in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and vtterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes it in all others: <hi>Pſa.</hi> 99.5. <hi>Habac.</hi> 1.13.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:16967:19"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the Mercy of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Mercie is a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in God, whereby hee pittieth his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in all their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and is ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them out of the ſame: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.8. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.4, 5.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the Iustice of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Iuſtice, or righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is a vertue in God, whereby he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth to all, according to his promiſe, for the good of the godly, and according to his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the wicked:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16967:20"/>
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.13. 1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the Love of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Love is a vertue in God, whereby he is infinitely delighted in himſelfe, and is ſo farre affected to his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as he is pleaſed to impart any goodneſſe unto them: <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.9.19.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Good Sir, I thanke you, for making me know God better than I did, by teaching mee his Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes; but now alſo I pray you teach me to ſerve God in reſpect of them; and therefore tell me what du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties I am to performe to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16967:20"/>God in reſpect of theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine faculties and powers, holy vertues and qualities in God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The duties of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice which you owe to God in reſpect of theſe Attributes of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are of two kindes: 1. Generall, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne them all. 2. Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, which belong to the ſeverall kindes of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I pray you what du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſervice muſt I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to God, in reſpect of his Attributes, both of Greatneſse and Goodneſſe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are two: 1. Admiring and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16967:21"/>all theſe perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and excellencies that are ſo infinitely in God: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.5. 2. Praiſing and extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, commending and magnifying God, in and for them: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 150.2. <hi>Revel.</hi> 5.11.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What ſpeciall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſervice to God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto him, in reſpect of his Attributes of Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſeverally?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are two: 1. an awefull reverence of the Majeſty, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious preſence of God, whereſoever wee bee: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.7. 2. Feare and trembling to offend this
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16967:21"/>great God by ſinne, in any time or place: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 39.9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.22.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And I pray you what ſpeciall duties of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to God must I doe vnto him, in reſpect of his Attributes of Goodneſſe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are two principally. 1. Faith, whereby wee beleeve whatſoever he ſpeakes, or writes, and alſo wee put truſt &amp; confidence in him for all good things which hee hath promiſed in his word, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.31. 2. Love, whereby our hearts are ſo knit vnto, and our
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16967:22"/>affections ſo ſet vpon God, that we deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than him, nor delight in nothing equall vnto him: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.1, 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 97.10.12.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, I heartily thank you for theſe ſavoury leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; the Lord bend my heart to practiſe theſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſervice which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne God immediately in reſpect of ſome things in himſelfe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Duties to God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately in reſpect of ſome things that come from him: as his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> 
                  <hi>you tolde me alſo of ſome other duties, that I am to doe, in reſpect of ſome things that proceede and come from him; what are theſe things I pray you, and what meane you by them?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:16967:22"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are either 1. his Ordinances; or 2. his Workes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What meane you by an Ordinance of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I meane, not a civill ordinance, as foode and phyſicke ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God for ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and bodily vſes and ends; but an holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance or meanes, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God, for ſpirituall and religious uſes and ends, (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) to beget and begin, to increaſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme grace and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then I pray you, what bee theſe holy and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16967:23"/>religious Ordinances of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They bee either 1. holy things, or 2. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly actions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the holy things which God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for holy vſes?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<note place="margin">The holy Scriptures.</note> or the holy wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Prophets and Apoſtles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to God muſt I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to him in reſpect of the holy Scriptures?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe foure. 1. Beleeving that the 39 Bookes of the Olde Teſtament, and the 28 of the New, were endi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16967:23"/>by Gods Spirit: 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. and that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine all truthes neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Gods ſervice, &amp; our ſalvation: 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.17. 2. Reading, ſearching and peruſing them, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.29. 3. Praiſe and thanks to God for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and keeping them vnto, and in his Church: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19, 20. 4. Deſire and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to vnderſtand, and make a right vſe of them for our direction, converſion, conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſatisfaction: <hi>Acts.</hi> 8.34. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:16967:24"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the holy actions ordained by God for holy vſes, in the doing of which I muſt ſerve God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Holy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes.</note> They are certaine religious exerciſes, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined, and ſpecially appointed by God, for holy vſes, (namely) the honour of God, &amp; edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of his Church, and for Gods publike ſervice; and they are theſe foure ſpecially: 1. Hearing the word, 2. receiving the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; 3. praying to God: 4. praiſing God. We ſerve God in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming any or all
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16967:24"/>theſe holy exerciſes, for God hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that they be done: But (beſides the doing of them) we are alſo to performe them in a manner preſcribed by God, and this manner of performing is ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to God alſo; and the duties that are to be done for this end, are ſuch as are either 1. common to all the four exerciſes; or 2. peculiar to each of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, common to them all?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold; for they concerne the time, either 1. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16967:25"/>wee come unto them; or 2. when we are in doing them; or 3. after wee haue done them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What dutie is to be done, before wee come to theſe religious exerciſes?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Wee muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelves to them and not come hand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver head: <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.1. and this wee ſhall doe, by conſidering, 1. that we which performe them are but duſt and aſhes, yea miſerable ſinners, and vnworthy to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them: 2. that herein wee have to doe with the great God of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16967:25"/>heaven and earth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.13: that we are in his ſpeciall preſence taking notice of vs, and our behaviour, <hi>Acts.</hi> 10.31: and that he <hi>will not hold vs guiltleſſe, if wee take his name in vaine, Exod.</hi> 20.7.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What dutie is to be done in the instant time we performe theſe religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous exerciſes?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Generally wee muſt performe them as God hath commanded both for ſubſtance and circumſtance, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.9. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8.5. Specially we muſt performe them with worſhip, and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16967:26"/>to God, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.29.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties are to bee done after wee have beene at theſe religious exerciſes?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>When wee have done and performed them, we muſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to be bettered by them, and remember to keepe our Covenant with God of ſerving him, (which wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to renew by our daily reſorting vnto them) and not returne to our former ſinnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.3. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20, 21. <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.14.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh Sir, you tolde
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16967:26"/>me even now, that when I ſerve God in doing religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous exerciſes to him, that I muſt alſo worſhip God at the ſame time; I would faine better vnderſtand what it is to worſhip God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What it is to worſhip God.</note> To worſhip God is to performe a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous exerciſe to God immediately, with an humble affection of our ſoule, and reverent ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of the body, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.6. Or, to humble the ſoule, and to bend the body im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to God for his honour, though we bee not in doing any ſuch ſpeciall religious
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16967:27"/>exerciſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.52. <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.31.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But I haue heard that to ſerve God, and to worſhip God are all one, are they not?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How it dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from the ſervice of God.</note> In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſpeech amongſt many, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God is taken for Gods worſhip; but in propriety of ſpeech, and in the nature of the thing they are not: for Gods ſervice is a more generall duty, and it is as much as obedience to God, and it reacheth unto all things that are to bee done, whether they be naturall and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, or holy and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16967:27"/>for in all theſe things wee muſt ſerve God. But the worſhip of God is but a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular duty, &amp; it is vſed onely in holy and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious actions and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes; and it is but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to one parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular commandement. 2. All worſhip com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by God is ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to him, in as much as it is an obedience to God which hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it: But all ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to God is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to God, as will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily appeare by this. Faithfulneſſe in our ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill calling is ſervice to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16967:28"/>God, becauſe it is obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God, who hath commanded it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.21. but it is not worſhip to <hi>God:</hi> becauſe worſhip to <hi>God</hi> is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in religious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions only, &amp; unto <hi>God</hi> only, &amp; that immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly only; but faithfulnes in our calling is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in civill actions, and mediately to men, our ſelves, or others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I pray you good Sir, make this a little more plaine unto me.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I will: you may better vnderſtand it, by a familiar compariſon, taken from the ſervice
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16967:28"/>of men. To ſerve a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is to doe as he bids him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.5. But to worſhip or reverence him, is to doe obeyſance to him, and to give him an humble and ſubmiſſiue reſpect, in looks, words and geſtures, of putting off the hat, making a leg, or the like: 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.20. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.46. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.26. <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.10.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, I thanke you; I now perceive cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the difference betwixt Gods ſervice, and worſhip: But now I pray you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede to the duties of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, which are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16967:29"/>to each of theſe foure religious exerciſes even now named, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the hearing of the word was the firſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tell mee what is that exerciſe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Duties in reſpect of hearing the word read and preached.</note> The hearing of the word is a part of Gods publike ſervice wherein wee diligently hearken and attend vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, whenſoever it is read, or preached and publiſhed, (that is) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and applyed vnto vs: <hi>Act.</hi> 16.14.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to God are we to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme at the hearing of the word?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:16967:29"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are of two kindes, for they belong to the hearing of it, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther firſt both read and preached, or preached onely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties belong to the hearing of the word, both read and preached too?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe ſixe. 1. Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt heeding, marking and minding of it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.46. 2. Beleeving or aſſenting to the truth of it, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.47. 3. Loving and delighting in it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.127.159. 4. Laying it vp in our hearts, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.18. 5. Keeping it in our hearts
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16967:30"/>
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 8.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.51. 6. Calling of it againe to minde and memory, and meditating vpon it, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.25. <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 1.8.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what duties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the hearing of the word preached onely?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are of two kindes, for they be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 1. common to all, and every part of the word preached; or 2. peculiar to ſome parts onely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the hearing of any and every part of the word preached?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe two: 1. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it not as the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16967:30"/>word of man, but of God, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13. 2. Examining our ſelves how wee profit by it, (that is) whether we be converted and ſaved by it, and whether wee be guilty of the ſins which it reproves, or doe the duties which it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, or be refreſhed with the comforts it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords, or bee terrified from ſinne, with the threatnings of it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall parts of the word that we muſt performe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties vnto, when they are preached?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are foure
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16967:31"/>chieſly: 1. the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of the word: 2. the promiſes: 3. the threatnings: 4. the good examples of the godly doings and ſufferings of godly perſons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the word?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of the word,
<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God.</note> are thoſe parts thereof which binde and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn the doing of good actions, and which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the committing of evill actions, in thought word and deede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what duties of ſervice to God, doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16967:31"/>concerne the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the word preached?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe three. 1. Obedience in doing the good actions com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and in leaving undone, and forbearing to doe the evill actions forbidden, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.24: and that for conſcience ſake, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 39.9. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.11: and conſtantly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. 2. Vſing al good means whereby wee may be furthered in our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.10.11. 3. Refraining all means occaſions and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16967:32"/>whereby wee may be hindered in our obedience, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.101.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the word?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the word.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Gods promiſes are thoſe parts of the word, wherein God covenants with his people, to beſtow upon them, (upon their faith and repentance) the things of this life, (that may be good for them) and of the life to come, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.10.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what duties doe properly belong to the promiſes of the word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:16967:32"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe foure. 1. Faith whereby wee beleeve the truth of them, and truſt in Gods power, goodneſſe and faithfulnes, for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of them, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. 2. Hope in God aſſuredly to looke for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.81. <hi>&amp;</hi> 42.5. 3. Ioy or rejoycing in the good things promiſed and hoped for, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.162. 4. Patience to waite Gods leiſure, till we be made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of them, without limiting God, the time or meanes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.36.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16967:33"/>
                  <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.25. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 123.2. <hi>Iſay</hi> 28.16.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the word?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Gods threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings are parts of his word,
<note place="margin">The threat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nings of the word.</note> wherein God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth to bring vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſinners, for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity and impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, temporall, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and eternall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what duties of ſervice to God, doe properly concerne theſe threatnings?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe two. 1. Trembling and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, at the very
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16967:33"/>hearing of them, <hi>Ier.</hi> 36.16.24. 2. Feare to ſinne againſt God, leſt the evills threatned in them, doe come vpon vs, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.4.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the word?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Certaine preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,
<note place="margin">The exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the word.</note> and particular patternes of the faith, obedience and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of Gods ſervants and children, recorded in the Bible.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties properly concerne theſe holy examples?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe two. 1. An honourable me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of them, and of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16967:34"/>their good name, ſeeing God was glorified by them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.16. 2. A ſincere purpoſe and endeavor, to imitate and follow their patternes, in the practiſe of the like du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.37. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.12.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, I thanke you for your labours touching my ſervice to God, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the firſt religious exerciſe, and part of Gods publike ſervice: I pray you goe on now with the ſecond, which is the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Sacraments: and firſt tell me what the receiving of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:16967:34"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Receiving the Sacraments,
<note place="margin">Duties in reſpect of receiving the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> is a part of Gods worſhip, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by taking certaine creatures, and uſing certaine actions about them, (appointed by God) and by ſetting them apart, by the word and prayer (from common and civill uſe to a ſacred uſe) there is thereby ſignified and remembred, Chriſt his death; and alſo the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits and merits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, are ſealed and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to all true belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.2, 3.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How many be there
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16967:35"/>of theſe Sacraments, that are to be received?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Two: 1. Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, 2. the Lords Supper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and ſervice to God, belong to the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of theſe Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They be of two ſorts. 1. Some which be common to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of both the Sacraments. Some that bee proper to each of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What be the duties that be common to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of both the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe two.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:16967:35"/>
               <p n="1">1. In reſpect of our bodies, wee muſt looke vpon the creatures and actions about them, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God to be uſed in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring of them for the remembring of Chriſt, and for the ſetting forth of his death; and wee muſt permit the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to adminiſter vnto us thoſe creatures and actions to this end; and alſo receive them from him, when they are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to vs by him, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.38. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.16, <hi>Ezra</hi> 6.21.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In reſpect of our ſoules; 1. wee muſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16967:36"/>on the nature and parts, uſe and end, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and comfort of the Sacraments. 2. We muſt remember with thankfulneſſe the death and blood-ſhedding of Chriſt ſhewed and ſet forth therein. 3. Wee muſt by faith apply to our ſelves the merits of Chriſts bloody death, to the waſhing away of our ſinnes, and to the nouriſhing of our ſouls in the life of grace, to the life of glory, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties to God are proper, to the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Sacrament of Baptiſme?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:16967:36"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe two. 1.
<note place="margin">Duties in reſpect of praying to God.</note> Deſire and endeavour, by prayer and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, to finde in our ſelves the efficacie and benefit thereof to the cleanſing of vs from the power and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our ſins, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4.2. Conſcience to doe what wee have profeſſed, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what wee have promiſed, (when wee were baptized) namely, to renounce the ſervice of ſinne, and to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue Gods faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. For hereby we ſhall manifeſt to our ſelves and others, that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16967:37"/>our ſoules are inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſpiritually bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with Chriſts blood and Spirit, as well as our bodies are out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly by the water and Miniſter, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.20, 21.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what duties are proper to the receiving of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The duties pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to that Sacrament have beene (as you know) plainely and largely delivered, by me in a Booke, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Spirituall exerciſe, to procure a good appetite un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and a good digestion of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16967:37"/>the Lords Supper;</hi> to which I referre you for more particular inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, I bleſſe God for theſe your directions, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the receiving of the Sacraments, which is the ſecond religious exerciſe of Gods publike ſervice: I pray you proceede to the third, which is Prayer, and therein firſt tell mee what it is?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Praying to God is a part of his publike ſervice, wherein we call vpon him, and beg of him, either the beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of good things up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, or the removing
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16967:38"/>of hurtfull things from us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties of ſervice concerne prayer to God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are of three kindes; for they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long either 1. to the matter of our prayers, or 2. to the manner; or 3. to the end of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the matter of our prayers, or the things wee pray for?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Two. 1. Wee muſt pray for ſuch things as bee in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves lawfull, and be warrantable by Gods word, <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.3. 2. We
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16967:38"/>muſt pray according to Gods will, (that is) for ſuch things, as may ſtand with Gods ſecret will in giving of them, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.39.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the manner of our praying?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe foure: we muſt pray, 1. with humility in conſcience of our unability and unworthineſſe to aske or receive, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.13. 2. with fervency in a ſenſible feeling of our want of the things wee beg, and in an earneſt deſire to enjoy them:
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:16967:39"/>3. with faith truſting in God, through Chriſt, for receiving what wee pray for, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.6.4. with patience waiting Gods leiſure and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, till wee be made partakers of that wee deſire and beg, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 40.1</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what duties concerne the end of our praing to God, or the cauſe why we pray?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe three. 1. In reſpect of God, wee muſt aime at this, that hee may bee glorified by his giving, and our receiving, &amp; u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the good things which we pray for, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16967:39"/>as hee is glorified by our ſeeking to him for them; for thereby wee acknowledge him to bee the giver of all, which is an honour to him, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In reſpect of our ſelves, wee are to pray for Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, not that we might ſpend them upon our ſinnes; but that in the uſe of them wee might bee furthered in Gods ſervice, <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In reſpect of our brethren, we muſt aime in our prayers that wee
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16967:40"/>may bee helpefull to them, and enabled by receiving good things from God, (through prayer) not to heape vp all for our ſelves and ours; but to diſtribute it amongſt Gods poore ſervants and children, that are in want, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their neede and our ability,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe are indeede holy and heavenly dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, concerning my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in praying to God, which is the third religious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe and part of Gods publike ſervice: But I pray you, let mee bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to you, for further
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:16967:40"/>instruction in the fourth and laſt, which is praiſing of God; and to tell mee firſt, what praiſing of God is?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Praiſing God,
<note place="margin">Duties in reſpect of praiſing God.</note> is a part of Gods pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſervice, wherein we magnifie, commend and extoll God, for thoſe excellent perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of greatneſſe and goodneſſe that are in him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 150.2: and alſo give him thankes for his benefits beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed upon us, <hi>Revel.</hi> 7.12.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to God concerne our praiſing him?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:16967:41"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are of two kindes; for they belong either 1. to the parts of our praiſing God; or 2. to the meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is performed, (namely) ſinging of Pſalmes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the parts of praiſing God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are theſe foure. 1. An high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme and opinion (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond that which wee are able to expreſſe) of the holy and happy perfections that are in God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.1.9. 2. A free acknowledgement of the receipt from his
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16967:41"/>bountifull hands, of all the good things we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.16. 3. An humble confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to receive any good things from God, or to returne any praiſe or thankes unto him, for the things we have received, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.10. 4. A full reſolution to uſe &amp; imploy all Gods bleſſings which hee gives vs, to his glory, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.9. to the good of others, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17. and our owne furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in godlines, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4, 5.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what duties
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:16967:42"/>of ſervi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to God, doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne our ſinging of Pſalmes?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Three eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. 1. For the matter which we muſt ſing, it muſt be holy and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall; not fooliſh and profane ſongs and bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lads, made by wicked men; but hymnes and pſalmes of Gods ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or according to them, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. 2. For our manner of ſinging, it muſt be with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and with an holy and ſanctified heart and affection, <hi>with grace in our hearts, Col.</hi> 3.16. 3. For our end in ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16967:42"/>it muſt bee, not to take pride in our owne ſweete voice and breſt, nor to pleaſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens eares, who are more delighted in the ſound and muſicke, than in the matter: but to <hi>make melodie in our hearts to God,</hi> and to comfort our ſelves in him, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I cannot but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, (good Sir) that you have beene ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry large and profitable in your Inſtructions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my duties of ſervice to God, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the firſt ſort of things that proceede from God,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16967:43"/>namely his ordinances, there remaines the ſecond ſort of things that proceed from God, and that is his workes, in reſpect whereof alſo I muſt ſerve God: I pray you therefore direct me herein alſo, and first tell me what theſe workes of God be?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Gods workes are either 1. generall, which have reſpect to all the world, as the creating, preſerving, and governing of all things therein, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36: Or 2. they are ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall workes of his, which concerne our ſelves, and which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16967:43"/>either from his mercy, as bleſſings; or from his juſtice, as croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and afflictions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to God belong to him in reſpect of theſe his workes?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are of 3.
<note place="margin">Duties in reſpect of Gods workes.</note> kindes; for they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne either 1. Gods generall workes on the whole world; or 2. Gods ſpeciall workes of mercy on our ſelves and others: or 3. Gods ſpeciall workes of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice on our ſelves and others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne Gods generall works
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16967:44"/>of creating, preſerving and governing the whole world?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe three. 1. We muſt looke upon them with our eyes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.1. <hi>Iob</hi> 36.24. 2. Wee muſt talke of them with our tongues, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.7. 3. With our mindes wee muſt take notice, and obſerve in theſe his workes, his infinite wiſedome, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and goodneſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20: and magnifie God for them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148.5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne Gods ſpeciall workes
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:16967:44"/>of mercy, or his bleſsings, on our ſelves or others?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p n="1">1. Thankfulneſſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.20. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.18. wherof you have heard in the ordinance of praiſing God. 2. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in God, and in the uſe and enjoying of his bleſſings, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.15. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.7.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what duties concerne Gods ſpeciall workes of justice, or affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions on our ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in reſpect of all afflictions on our ſelves, we muſt 1 meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:16967:45"/>ſubject our ſelves with patience to beare them, in conſideration, 1. that they are <hi>Gods hand</hi> on vs, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.18. which we cannot reſiſt <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.9. 2. That they are juſtly deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by our <hi>ſinnes, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah</hi> 7.9. 3. That we are not alone therein; but have many fellowes in <hi>temptations common to men,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.14. 4. That after them there is a <hi>reſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared</hi> for them that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure them, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.13. 5. That God will either give us aſſiſtance in the tryall,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:16967:45"/>or <hi>deliverance out of it,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. 2. Wee muſt wiſely endeavour to profit by them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life, and new obedience, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.11.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in reſpect of all afflictions on our brethren, wee muſt 1. have a fellow-feeling of the ſame upon them, as if they were on our ſelves, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. 2. We muſt pray for them, for their eaſe, remedy and deliverance, if it bee Gods will; or a ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied uſe of them, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.13. 3.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:16967:46"/>We muſt helpe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve them in the ſame (as we are able) and to deliver them out of the ſame, <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.14. <hi>Iob</hi> 31.20.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in reſpect of ſome temptations and afflictions that have beene ſanctified to us, or our bretheren, ſo that wee have received from them, (through Gods good grace) ſome holy fruit of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wee muſt 1. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 119.69.71. 2. We muſt bleſſe God for them, <hi>Iob</hi> 1.21. 3. We
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:16967:46"/>muſt rejoyce and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our ſelves in them, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.2, 3. becauſe 1. they are not Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, but chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.5. 2. They come from God not as an enemy, but as a father reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Chriſt, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Hebr:</hi> 12.5. 3. God is moved to ſend them in love, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.9. and that they ſhall not ſeparate us fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the love of God in Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38, 39. 4. God aymed in theſe afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at ſome ſpirituall good, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10. 5. The event of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:16967:47"/>them ſhall be their and our furtherance in grace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.71. <hi>&amp;</hi> 37.37, <hi>unto ſalvation, Phil.</hi> 1.19.28.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, you have beene very large and long, (to your great paines) in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching mee how to ſerve God, with duties that have reſpect to himſelfe in conſideration of his divine Attributes that bee in him, and alſo of his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and workes procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from him: I pray you proceede to my duties unto my Neighbour.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are of 2. kindes; 1. ſuch as are common to all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:16967:47"/>one: 2. ſuch as are peculiar to ſome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are thoſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to all?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are 1. ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, namely 1. to love our neighbour as our ſelves, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.39: 2. to doe unto him as we (being guided by true reaſon) would have him to doe to us, <hi>Math.</hi> 7.12. 2. ſpecial, which are five.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which are they?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The firſt is to maintaine his place and authority, office and preheminence, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, Church or family, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.12.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:16967:48"/>which is the 5. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is to preſerve his life, health, and bodily ſtrength, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.13. which is the 6. Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>The third is to che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the chaſtity of our neighbour, and neither by lookes or geſtures, words or actions, to aſſault or violate the ſame, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.14. which is the 7. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</p>
               <p>The fourth is, to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the profit and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gaine of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and in nothing of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:16967:48"/>the leaſt worth to ſeeke his loſſe and dammage, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.15. which is the 8. Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>The fifth is, to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his credit and good name, and not to diſgrace him, by word or action in the leaſt manner or meaſure, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.16. which is the 9. Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are thoſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that are peculiar to ſome of our Neighbours?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p n="1">1. Such as are due to godly and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtians, as namely, 1. brotherly
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:16967:49"/>love and religious af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.1: when wee therefore love them, not becauſe they are men, or our kindred, or beneficiall to us; but becauſe of their graces, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian vertues eminent in them. 2. Patience to beare with their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and cover their infirmities, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.8. 2. Such as are due to ſome, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as they are tyed to us by any bond of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or law, as hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands and wives, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents or children, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters or Servants, or the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:16967:49"/>like: of which duties you may reade at large in a booke made by D. <hi>Gouge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D <hi>Gouge</hi> of Houſhold duties.</note> who hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten fully, and to excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent purpoſe thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, my deſire is to know and doe the whole revealed will of God, and therefore as you have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed mee in my dutie,</hi> 1. <hi>in reſpect of God, and</hi> 2. <hi>in reſpect of my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: ſo I beſeech you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to tell mee in the third place, what is my dutie of ſervice unto God, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of my ſelfe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I will: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you conſiſt both of a body, and of a
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:16967:50"/>ſoule,
<note place="margin">Duties in reſpect of our ſelves.</note> and have a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble calling to live in, namely a civill calling, and a Chriſtian calling; therefore will I briefly ſhew you the ſumme of your dutie in reſpect of all foure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir I thanke you, I pray you then ſhew me my duty in reſpect of my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It is this, to <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe your veſſel in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and honour,</hi> (that is) in chaſtity, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and ſobriety, without pride or lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury, chambering or wantonneſſe, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reſtraining the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:16967:50"/>parts and members thereof, from being weapons and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to let in, or let out ſinne; and withhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them from the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of doing evill, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.4, 5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12 <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is my dutie in reſpect of my ſoule?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>To be watchfull over it, and over all the powers and faculties thereof, that you grow not looſe or ſecure in ſinne; yea to bee cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect in all your wayes, that you be not deceived by your own
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:16967:51"/>deceitfull heart, the worlds vanities, and Satans ſubtleties, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.23. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.13. <hi>to</hi> 19.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to me in my Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an calling?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe ſeven chiefly.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To bee zealous and diſcreete, humble and ſincere, in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Daily to repent of our ſinnes, and to cry God mercie by faith in Chriſt, as wee
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:16967:51"/>ſinne daily, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.12.</p>
               <p n="3">3. So to live, as thoſe that looke to die, and to riſe unto judgement, at the ſecond comming of Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30, 31. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.17, 18. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.29.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To mortifie our ſinfull and corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, 1. by applying to our ſelves the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and threatnings of the word, <hi>Col:</hi> 3.5: and 2: by denying to our ſelves all occaſions, meanes and opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſinne, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.29, 30.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:16967:52"/>
               <p n="5">5. To moderate our deſires to the profits, pleaſures and honours of the world, (conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the vanity of them <hi>Eccleſ:</hi> 1.2) and not to be diſcontent with our preſent ſtate, nor to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet our neighbours, <hi>Hebr:</hi> 13.5. <hi>Tit:</hi> 2.12. <hi>Exod:</hi> 12.17. <hi>Rom:</hi> 7.7.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To make ſure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſelves, our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, election and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, by growing in the number and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Chriſtian gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, 2 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.</p>
               <p n="7">7. To ſtrive and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to continue
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:16967:52"/>and perſevere in well-doing, and patient ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for conſcience ſake, <hi>Matth:</hi> 10.22. <hi>Iam:</hi> 1.25. <hi>Rev:</hi> 2.25. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And I pray you (good Sir) what duties appertaine to mee in my civill calling, courſe, and trade of life?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe ſeven prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Diligence &amp; pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe without idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.7, 8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Cheerefulnes and joyfulnes, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weary of well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Deut:</hi> 12.7.2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:16967:53"/>
               <p n="3">3. Moderation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out plodding and moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, carking and caring (through diſtruſt) to the neglect of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily health and ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Matth:</hi> 6.33.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Honeſty and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, without wronging others, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving them, 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 4.6.12.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Charity, in ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not our owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and good onely, and to be all for our ſelves, but the benefit of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Phil:</hi> 2.4. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 10.33.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Sincerity, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:16967:53"/>the duties of our callings, not as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men onely, and to be ſeene of them; but as unto God, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove our ſelves to him <hi>Col:</hi> 3.22, 23.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Piety in going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, not in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of our owne wiſedome, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.5; but with praier to God in affiance of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>Geneſ:</hi> 24.42.48. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.6.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh good Sir, this is abundantly enough to teach mee to know what Gods ſervice is, &amp; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it doth conſiſt: now I pray you affect mee with
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:16967:54"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:16967:54"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:16967:55"/>Gods ſervice, and teach me how to be affected, and in love with it?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I will:
<note place="margin">Seeking to be affected with Gods ſervice.</note> for what good will it doe you to know what Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is, except you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſerve God. For this end therefore you muſt know &amp; beleeve, conſider and lay to heart, certaine motives concerning his ſervice, that may ſtirre you up to deſire, love and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it; and they are theſe five; 1. the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of ſerving God; 2. the neceſſity of it; 3. the excellency of it; 4. the equity of it; and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:16967:55"/>5. the reward of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of Gods ſervice ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, and that it is poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for us to ſerve God here in this world?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Two wayes: 1. by the promiſe of the Spirit to be given to them that ſeek it, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee will <hi>put Gods lawes in their hearts, and write them in their inner parts</hi> for his obedience and ſervice, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. <hi>Ezek:</hi> 11.19. <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.33. 2. By the many exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of godly men, who have beene called by God himſelfe, his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, as <hi>Moſes, Ioſh.</hi> 1.1.
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:16967:56"/>
                  <hi>Ioſhuah: ch.</hi> 24.29: <hi>Iob, ch.</hi> 1.8: <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 18.1: <hi>Iſaiah, ch.</hi> 20.3: <hi>Zerubbabel, Hag:</hi> 2.23: and others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity of the ſervice of God bee made plaine unto me?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>By conſidering 1. the commandement of God, which enjoyns it often and earneſtly in his word, <hi>Deut:</hi> 10.12.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.4. <hi>Ioſh:</hi> 24.24. 2. The danger of not ſerving God, for they who neglect it are guiltie of great ſinnes, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 10.6. <hi>Nehem:</hi> 9.35. and are
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:16967:56"/>lyable to greater pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments. <hi>Deut,</hi> 28.47. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.8. and 6.21.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the ſervice of God be proved?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>By knowing and laying to heart, 1 That it is no baſe or meane thing, to be Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant: but that it is an honour, and a great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Ioſu.</hi> 1.2. 2. That Gods ſervice is not a bondage but a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.22. 3. That God is the beſt Lord and Maſter to ſerve, and that his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges is the beſt reward, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt pay, <hi>Deu:</hi> 10.20 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.24.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:16967:57"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may the equity of Gods ſervice appeare?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It will eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that it is equall &amp; juſt you ſhould ſerue God if you conſider: 1. That God, deſerues it of you by his many benefits beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, as namely your creation, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 100, 2. and your preſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 24 17: but ſpecially your ſalvation: <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.74.75 2. That before your converſion unto him, you haue made God <hi>to ſerue with your ſinnes, Iſai,</hi> 43.24. 3. That before your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verſion you ſerved the world,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:16967:57"/>the Devill, and your owne luſts for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of your life, &amp; too long; and that now you know not how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle tyme you haue to ſerve him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 44.6.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the reward of Gods ſervice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It is this: God will not onely graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly accept of our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 40.41. paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by the failings of it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.18: But will alſo beſtowe upon his faithfull ſervants, 1 Temporall things: as long life, health, wealth, children, and a good
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:16967:58"/>name, <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.9. &amp; 42.10 <hi>Deut:</hi> 28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112. and 128.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Spiritual, as increaſe of grace, and peace, joy, and comfort of a good conſcience: <hi>Prov:</hi> 15.15: <hi>Pſ:</hi> 119 <hi>Iſai</hi> 56.6: 7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Eternall, which is deliverance from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall miſery, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of all like happineſſe and glory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Math:</hi> 25.34.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe are indeede powerfull mot ves to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Chriſtians to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with Gods ſervice, and (I bleſſe God) I am much moved therewith:
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:16967:58"/>but one thing is yet want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof you told me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, which is the third and laſt th ng in ſeeking to ſerve God, namely, Seeking to performe and practiſe it; I pray you inſtruct mee therein alſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I will, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there is good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you ſhould learne this leſſon too,
<note place="margin">Seeking to practiſe the ſervice of God.</note> becauſe the end of your deſire of Gods ſervice is to practiſe it, and it had beene better for you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to have beene affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the love and liking of Gods ſervice, if you do not performe it to God accordingly.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:16967:59"/>Now then in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance and practiſe of Gods ſervice, theſe foure things are to be conſidered and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: 1, the manner how: 2, the meaſure where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: 3, the end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: and 4, the meanes whereby it is to bee done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir I thanke you, and I pray you further inſtruct mee in each of them, for they are materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all points indeed; and firſt tell mee in what manner the ſervice of God is to be performed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The manner of performing ſervice and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:16967:59"/>obedience to God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in theſe ſixe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars chiefly:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Vnderſtandingly, with knowledge and judgement, 1 <hi>Chron:</hi> 28.9. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 47.7. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 14.15.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Humbly, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our unability and unworthineſſe to ſerve him, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.19.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Faithfully, with affiance and truſt in Gods mercy through Chriſts merits for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, laying holde on the covenant of grace, <hi>Col:</hi> 1.17. <hi>Iſay</hi> 56.6.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Conſcionably, in
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:16967:60"/>obedience to God, who in his word wills and commands us to ſerve him, <hi>Acts</hi> 23.1. <hi>Iam:</hi> 2.11.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Holily, with a religious, godly and heavenly mind in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit and life, <hi>Rom:</hi> 12.1. <hi>&amp; chap:</hi> 7.6.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Sincerely, and with an upright and honeſt heart, 1 <hi>Chron:</hi> 28.9. <hi>Ioſh:</hi> 24.14. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>In what meaſure is our ſervice to God to bee performed?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The meaſure in which the ſervice of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:16967:60"/>God is to bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, may thus be laid downe on this manner:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Generally, wee muſt ſerve God with all our might, (that is) with all the parts and members of our bodies &amp; with al the powers &amp; faculties of our ſoules, <hi>Deut:</hi> 6.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.12. <hi>Ioſh:</hi> 14.8. <hi>Num.</hi> 14.24.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And more ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally wee muſt ſerve God, as touching the meaſure:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Cheerfully, &amp; with a willing mind, <hi>Iſay</hi> 58.13. 1 <hi>Chron:</hi> 28.9. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 40.7, 8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Ioyfully, and with
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:16967:61"/>a glad heart, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 100. 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 119.132.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Zealouſly, and with earneſt affection, and devotion, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.20. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.2.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Conſtantly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, and with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance unto the end, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.74, 75. 1 <hi>Chron:</hi> 28.7.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh this conſtancy and perſeverance is a rare grace indeed, but I feele my heart very fleeting and unſetled; I pray you how may I get to continue in the ſerving and obeying of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>For this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:16967:61"/>you muſt do theſe things:</p>
               <p n="1">1. You muſt <hi>give</hi> &amp; conſecrate <hi>your ſelfe</hi> to Gods ſervice, <hi>Rom:</hi> 6.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.1. <hi>Set your heart and ſoule to ſeeke God, Deut:</hi> 32.46. and to <hi>obey his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Deut:</hi> 32.46. <hi>Yeeld your ſelfe to the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 30.8. and <hi>ſubſcribe unto him, Iſay</hi> 44.5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You muſt be roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and grounded in the knowledge &amp; love of Gods ſervice, <hi>Deut:</hi> 10.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.13. <hi>Iſay</hi> 56.6. <hi>Eph:</hi> 3.17. 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 2.10.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:16967:62"/>
               <p n="3">3. You muſt often renew your promiſe and purpoſe, vowe, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and oath of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 119.106. <hi>&amp;</hi> 39.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 61.8. <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.3. 2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 15.32.</p>
               <p n="4">4. You muſt not be formall and ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all onely in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, to doe it publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Church one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or privately in the family onely, where o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may ſee you; but ſecretly in your cloſet, where none is preſent but God; and you muſt ſerve God with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of your minde,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:16967:62"/>and affection of your heart, carefully &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionably, 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3.5. <hi>Tit:</hi> 1.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 23.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 26.7.</p>
               <p n="5">5. You muſt be jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and ſuſpicious of your ſelfe, leſt there be in you a deceitfull and an <hi>vnfaithfull heart to withdraw</hi> you from Gods ſervice, <hi>Hebr:</hi> 3.13.</p>
               <p n="6">6. You muſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of apoſtacy, and the benefit of perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in Gods ſervice, 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2.20, 21. <hi>Heb:</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. <hi>chapters: Matth:</hi> 10.22. <hi>Revel:</hi> 2.10.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:16967:63"/>
               <p n="7">7. You muſt pray to God to <hi>keepe you in his name, Ioh.</hi> 17.11. <hi>Iude</hi> 24 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.8, 9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I pray you good Sir, now ſhew me the end why I must ſerve God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Not to be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified and ſaved there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, for this is to worke for wages as a baſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and not as a good ſonne; nor yet out of any carnall worldly ends or reſpects, as vaine glory, and the good opinion of men, or worldly profit; but for a threefold end.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In reſpect of God, that hee may be glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:16967:63"/>thereby, whoſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice it is by appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to whom it is to bee performed, <hi>Matth:</hi> 5.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In reſpect of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that they may be either wonne to the ſame ſervice with us, or confirmed in it, 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 3.5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In reſpect of our ſelves, that wee may make good proofe of the truth of our faith, and thereby make ſure unto our ſelves the good will of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, and that hee meanes to ſave us, <hi>Rom:</hi> 12.1, 2.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:16967:64"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P:</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now in the last place I pray you ſhew me, the meanes whereby I may come to practiſe this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M:</speaker>
               <p>That you may indeede practiſe Gods ſervice which you knowe and affect, you muſt doe theſe things: 1. You muſt put away, renounce and wholly leave, &amp; ſhake off your former ſervice of ſin, the world, and Satan: 1 <hi>Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> 7:3: elſe you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſerue God: <hi>Ioſua</hi> 24 19: You muſt be <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from dead works: Heb</hi> 9:14. you <hi>must dye to ſinne,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. <hi>Put off
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:16967:64"/>the old man. Eph.</hi> 4.22.23. 2 You muſt ſeeke to God for grace to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able you to ſerve him. <hi>Heb:</hi> 12.28. 3. You muſt ſtirre up the grace of God in you, &amp; when you have received it, you muſt uſe it well, 2. <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.20.22.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may we bee moved to leave the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of ſinne, Satan, &amp; the world?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>By beleeving, and laying to heart, remembring and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the ſinneful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and damnable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that ſervice,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:16967:65"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:16967:65"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:16967:66"/>together with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, &amp; remedy, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee have heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the motives to Gods ſervice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may I be moved to ſeek to God for grace, to enable me to his ſervice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p n="1">1. By knowing and feeling your neede of grace, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it you are unable to ſerve God, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.10. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.5. 2. By beleeving, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the ſufficiency and eſſicacie of grace, to enable you to ſerve God, and to abide in you, and to keepe you
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:16967:66"/>in his ſervice, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.9. <hi>I Ioh:</hi> 2.27. <hi>Ioh:</hi> 4.14.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may I be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up, well to uſe the grace of God when I have received it?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>By conſidering, 1. that the grace of God is given to you for this end, namely, that you might ſerve God with it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28 <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.13. 2. that God is worthy to be ſerved with the grace which himſelfe hath given; for without him we can doe nothing that good is, <hi>Revel:</hi> 4. 3. That if you will uſe a little
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:16967:67"/>meaſure of grace, and ſtirre vp your ſelfe to ſerue God with it, then ſhall your talent hereof increaſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.20.21</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir I humbly thanke you for your paynes with me, and patience towards me. I am loth to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bold with you at once, and to interrupt your ſtudies too long: I hope it will not bee offenſiue to you if when I haue ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ciently thought vpon theſe your instructions touching ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to ſerue God, (which is the firſt thing you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded unto me:) if at another time. I repaire un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, in the ſecond, which
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:16967:67"/>is, ſeeking to be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhall bee welcome, if you come at the beginning of the weeke, at which time, I haue moſt lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. In the meane time, the Lord be with you, and bleſſe my labours, for the furtherance of you, &amp; the reſt of my people, in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſalvation, by Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16967:68"/>
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:16967:68"/>
            <head>SEEKING to bee ſaved, <hi>when we dye.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Minister.</speaker>
               <p>VVEll met (good Neighbour:) how have you done, ſince you were with me laſt, and how doth your family?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pariſhioner.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The beter for you (Sir, I praiſe God) and for your
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:16967:69"/>good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſtructions you gaue me.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Much good may they doe you. I deſire, that God may haue the praiſe of them, and you the profit: I hope, that at leaſt, you remember what was the ſumme of our conference then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I were much to blame, if I ſhould forget that, being a point that ſo neerely concerned me, and which you handled ſo largely: (By your favour) it was this,</hi> that I ought to ſeeke to ſerve God, while I live <hi>in this world. But (good Sir)
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:16967:69"/>you mentioned there ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther duty like unto this, which I greatly deſire you would inſtruct mee in at your convenient leiſure: If I ſhould not be too tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, I would reſort unto you at the beginning of the weeke for further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in that alſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhall not bee troubleſome, but welcome; I would I had in my Pariſh more of your minde, for then ſhould I conceive hope that they minded good things, ſeeing they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired after them, and repaired unto mee for private information, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:16967:70"/>and above my pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Miniſtery. If you will (Neighbour) goe home with mee now, and wee will conferre together about it. But can you tell mee, what that ſecond point of Chriſtian duty was?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes that I can, I thanke God; though my memory be bad enough: It was this, I take it;</hi> I muſt ſeeke to be ſaved when I die. <hi>Me thinkes it is a neceſſary duty, and it is good reaſon I ſhould practiſe it: but I would faine have ſome good ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, to binde mee to the practiſe of it, that I
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:16967:70"/>might not faile to doe it, being ſo needfull.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I will ſatisfie your deſire, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound unto you to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of this duty, ſhall be drawne into ſome heads, for the helpe of your memory. The heads are foure: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the firſt concernes God; the ſecond your ſelfe; the third other men; and the fourth hath reſpect unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation it ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which bee thoſe reaſons that concern God, and which may perſwade
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:16967:71"/>me to ſeeke to bee ſaved?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are three.
<note place="margin">That Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt ſeeke to be ſaued, and why.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt is taken from Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, that biddes Chriſtians <hi>to ſeeke the Kingdome of God, and his righteouſneſſe;</hi> yea to ſeeke it <hi>first,</hi> (that is) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore &amp; above al world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, <hi>Matth:</hi> 6.33: <hi>To ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait gate, Luke</hi> 13.24: <hi>To labour for the meate, that endures to eternall life, Iohn</hi> 6.27: and to <hi>labour to enter into that reſt, Hebr:</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p>The ſecond reaſon is drawne from Gods promiſe,
<note place="margin">Why Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt ſeeke to be ſaued.</note> which is 1. in
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:16967:71"/>generall, that <hi>they which ſeeke ſhall finde, Matth:</hi> 7.7. 2. in ſpeciall, that <hi>they which ſeeke the Lord ſhall finde him, Ier:</hi> 29.13. 3. and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, that <hi>they which ſeeke Gods Kingdome, it will be their Fathers pleaſure to give it unto them, Luke</hi> 12.31, 32.</p>
               <p>The third argument is taken from Gods dealing with ſinners, in his ſeeking that they might be ſaved. For 1. God the Father ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulates with ſinners, <hi>why they will dye,</hi> and not be ſaved, <hi>Ezck:</hi> 33.11: yea he <hi>intreates</hi> (by his
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:16967:72"/>Miniſters) <hi>that they would bee reconciled to God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. 2. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt came to <hi>ſeek and ſave loſt ſinners, Luk:</hi> 19.10: yea hee invites them to <hi>come unto him,</hi> (that is) to beleeve in him, that they may be <hi>eaſed,</hi> and ſaved, <hi>Matth:</hi> 11.28. <hi>Ioh:</hi> 6.35. And 3. the Holy Ghoſt <hi>ſtrives</hi> with them by exhortations, <hi>Gen:</hi> 6.3: and <hi>teſtifies</hi> to them, (that is) forewarnes and chargeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, that they would bee converted, to the end they may be ſaved, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.30. 1 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 4.6.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:16967:72"/>Now there is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that God ſhould ſeeke to us to be ſaved; and not we to him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the reaſon that concernes our ſelves, that may move us to ſeeke to be ſaved?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It is this: wee muſt ſeeke to be ſaved, becauſe wee neede to ſeeke it, and we neede to ſeeke for ſalvation; partly, becauſe we are (by nature) ignorant of the way thereunto, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1.22, 23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.14: (and the Divell ſeekes to keepe us in this ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4.4:) partly, becauſe ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:16967:73"/>will not be obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned without diligent ſeeking, for <hi>the violent take it by force, Matth:</hi> 11.12: and partly alſo, becauſe, if we doe <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to ſeeke ſalvation,</hi> we ſinne fearefully, and cannot <hi>eſcape condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Hebr:</hi> 2.4. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the reaſon to perſwade me to ſeeke for ſalvation, that is taken from other men?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It is this. Firſt, Gods Miniſters doe <hi>ſeeke</hi> us, that we might be ſaved, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.14. for <hi>they beſeech us to bee reconciled to God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor:</hi>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:16967:73"/>5.20: they exhort us to <hi>ſave our ſelves from the wicked generation of this world, Acts</hi> 2.40: yea <hi>their hearts deſire and prayer to God for us is, that we might bee ſaved, Rom:</hi> 10.1. And there is no reaſon, that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhould bee more carefull of our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than wee of our owne. Secondly, the Church of God in all ages, hath afforded ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny memorable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of holy people that have ſought for ſalvation, and found it, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.30. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.6.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:16967:74"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the fourth and laſt reaſon, taken from ſome conſideration concerning ſalvation it ſelfe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It is this: You ought to ſeeke for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, becauſe it is worth your ſeeking; for it is called by way of excellency, <hi>ſo great ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, Hebr:</hi> 2.4: <hi>the ſalvation of God, Acts</hi> 23.28: yea <hi>ſalvation with eternall glory,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.10</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe indeed are good arguments to prove, both that I must ſeeke it, and why I must: but when muſt I ſeeke it?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Though I ſay
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:16967:74"/>you muſt ſeeke to bee ſaved when you dye; I doe not meane, you muſt ſeeke when you dye; but that you muſt ſeeke to bee ſaved, while you live. You muſt <hi>ſeeke God while hee may be found, Iſay.</hi> 55.5: and God will be found in this life; for <hi>now is the day of ſalvation, now is the accepted time,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 6.3: for now the means of grace are afforded unto us, in the uſe of Gods ordinances, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that end. <hi>Dives</hi> was carryed to <hi>hell</hi> when he dyed; and out of it there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:16967:75"/>
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 16.23.26. The fooliſh vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins wanting oyle in their lampes, when the bridegroome came, were ſhut out of the bride-chamber, though then they deſired to get oyle, <hi>Math.</hi> 25.12.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But I pray you (good Sir) how, and by what meanes may I ſeeke for ſalvation?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Even in the ſame manner,
<note place="margin">How Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt ſeeke to be ſaued.</note> and by the ſame meanes, that I taught you to ſeeke to ſerve God; namely by ſeeking 1. to know the chiefe points of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of ſalvation: 2. to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:16967:75"/>affect and deſire it: 3. to get and obtaine ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I pray you then Sir in the firſt place tell me, what are the chiefe poynts of the doctrine of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that are to be knowne.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are three,
<note place="margin">To know the chiefe points of ſalvation.</note> for we muſt knowe &amp; beleeue: 1. What it is to bee ſaved, and this wee may knowe, for God hath ordayned meanes <hi>to giue vs know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſalvation, Luk.</hi> 1.77. <hi>And to ſhew us the way of it. Act,</hi> 16.17.2. The ſeverall degrees, by which ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is attayned,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:16967:76"/>which is not all at once: 3. The meanes whereby it is effected and brought to paſſe, in theſe ſeverall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, (I thinke) I knowe already the firſt poynt, which is, what it is to be ſaved, (namely) it is to bee freed from hell and damnation.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It is ſome thing which you ſay; but that is not all. For to bee ſaved is not onely to bee freed from all eternall curſſedneſſe, which is to <hi>eſcape the damnation of hell: Math.</hi> 23, 33. to <hi>be delivered
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:16967:76"/>from the wrath to come,</hi> 1, <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.10: to <hi>haue your ſoule ſaved from death eternall: Iam:</hi> 5.20: and to be kept that <hi>yee periſh not,</hi> nor <hi>be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, Iohn</hi> 3:16, 17. But to bee ſaved is to partake of all eternall bleſſedneſſe in another life and world, which is, to <hi>obtaine eternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> 2. <hi>Tim:</hi> 2:10: to <hi>inherit the kingdome of God, Math:</hi> 25:34: to <hi>enter into our Masters joy: Math:</hi> 25.34: to bee <hi>ever with the Lord Christ:</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l:</hi> 1, 23: namely, to <hi>behold</hi> and partake of
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:16967:77"/>
                  <hi>his glory, Iohn</hi> 17.24.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I perceive now my failing, and it must needs be ſo, as you ſay, touching the nature of ſalvation: but I pray you alſo proceed to the ſecond general point of the doctrine of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſhew me what are the degrees, by which it is attained.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are three.
<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of ſaluation.</note> 1. In this life, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.9. 2. At the end of this life, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.59. 3. At the end of the world, <hi>Hebr:</hi> 9.28.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What degree of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is attained unto in this life?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It hath three branches.</p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:16967:77"/>
               <p n="1">1. Iuſtification, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the faithfull are ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acquitted and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, from the guilt and puniſhment of all their ſinnes, by free pardon and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of them all, and whereby alſo they are accepted as righteous in Gods ſight by the merit of Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, both of his life &amp; death imputed unto them, <hi>Mat:</hi> 9.2. <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.6, 7. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Reconciliation, whereby ſinners being freed from Gods anger and diſpleaſure, juſtly incurred and provoked
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:16967:78"/>by their ſinnes, they are againe received into his love, favour, and friendſhip, <hi>Matth:</hi> 3.17. <hi>Col:</hi> 1.21.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Adoption, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by of the <hi>children of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ence, of wrath, and of the Divell,</hi> (which they were in <hi>Adam,</hi> and by their ſinnes, <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 2.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.6. <hi>Ioh:</hi> 8.44) they are made <hi>the children of God, and heires of the Kingdome of heaven, Gal:</hi> 4.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.6. <hi>Eph:</hi> 1.4, 5, 6.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What degree of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation doe the faithfull attaine at the end of this life?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:16967:78"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It is this. Firſt, and generally, they <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part in peace, Luke</hi> 2.29: for their ſoules are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from their bodies in Gods favour; they are <hi>carried</hi> to heaven, <hi>Luk:</hi> 16.22. and <hi>received</hi> thither, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.50: <hi>They dye in Christ,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 4.16: they <hi>ſleepe in Ieſus, verſe</hi> 24: they <hi>dye in the Lord, Revel:</hi> 14.13: they <hi>dye the death of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, Num:</hi> 23.10: they <hi>depart to the Father, Iohn</hi> 13:1. As ſoone as they are departed this life, their ſoules are <hi>with Chriſt in Paradiſe,</hi> which is Chriſts <hi>Kingdome,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:16967:79"/>Luke</hi> 23.42.43: even when their bodies are unburied, or lye in the grave: and therefore this ſalvation is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>ſalvation of the ſoule,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.9. <hi>Heb:</hi> 10.39: for the <hi>ſpirits of juſt and perfect men are in heaven, Hebr:</hi> 12.25. And well may the faithfull <hi>depart in peace</hi> when they dye, ſeeing when they lived they were <hi>juſtified by faith, and had peace with God, Rom.</hi> 5.1: Good cauſe have they, (if they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not to conſider it) not to feare to dye, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they know, that the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:16967:79"/>
                  <hi>ſting of their death is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15.55, by Chriſt, who <hi>through his death hath overcome him that had the power of death, (that is) the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, Hebr:</hi> 2.14: and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are <hi>perſwaded that death ſhall not ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them from the love of God which is in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, Rom:</hi> 8.38, 39.</p>
               <p>Secondly, and more ſpecially: 1. The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the faithfull at the end of this life, are <hi>at rest from their labours</hi> paines and diſeaſes, and are free from ſenſe of all miſeries and vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Revel:</hi> 14.13. <hi>Iſai:</hi>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:16967:80"/>56.1, 2. 2. Their ſoules are wholly freed from originall and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall corruption; for the fleſh which was therein while they liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is wholly killed &amp; deſtroyed. For they are carryed into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Luk:</hi> 16, 22. into which <hi>no uncleane thing can enter: Revel:</hi> 21:27. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15.50.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of ſalvation doe the faithfull attaine unto at the end of the world?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It conſiſts of 2 branches, whereof the firſt concernes the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; the ſecond belongs
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:16967:80"/>to the ſoule and bodie too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What happines re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the body at the end of the world?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It is this: Of a naturall, dead, weake, corruptible, and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall body, (which it was when it was alive in the world, and lay in the grave) it is raiſed a ſpiritual, living, ſtrong, incorruptible, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall body; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing raiſed from death to life, it is reſtored to its former being and ſhape, complexion and proportion, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any defect or ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:16967:81"/>in a moſt comely manner; for it is a <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified body,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15.42. to 46.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yea but it ſeemes to naturall reaſon an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible thing, for a dead body to riſe and live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>True: but Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians know by the light of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that the dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhall riſe from death to life, not by any po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in it ſelfe, or by the meanes of any naturall cauſe; but by a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall, even the <hi>power of God, Matth:</hi> 22.29. <hi>Ioſh:</hi> 22.1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.16.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:16967:81"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may I bee drawne better to beleeve the Reſurrection from the dead?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>By theſe ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The teſtimony of Chriſt, who ſayd, that all <hi>that are in the graves ſhall heare Christs voyce, and come forth unto the Reſurrection: Iohn</hi> 5, 28 29.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The <hi>promiſe</hi> of it made by God unto the Patriarks, <hi>Act,</hi> 26:6:7:8.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The faith &amp; hope of Gods children, who in all ages beleeved it, hoped and lookt for it,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:16967:82"/>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 23:6: &amp; 24:15. <hi>Iohn</hi> 11:24.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The practiſe of many Heathen, who in hope of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>waſhed</hi> the dead bodyes of their freinds departed, before they buryed them, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15:29. <hi>&amp; Acts</hi> 9:36.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The proofe and experience of many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who have riſen from death to life, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27:52:53. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11:35.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The <hi>appoynting of a day of iudgment,</hi> at the <hi>ſecond comming of Chriſt: Act:</hi> 17.30, 31, 32. <hi>Ioh:</hi> 5:28:29. <hi>Dan:</hi> 12.2.</p>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:16967:82"/>
               <p n="7">7 The Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt himſelfe from death to life, to be the <hi>first fruits of them that ſleepe:</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15: 20. 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 4:14. 1: <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.3. For the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering in of the firſt ripe fruites, doe giue hope to the husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, of ripening &amp; ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering in of the reſt afterwards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Indeed theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons cleerely and unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably doe prove that the dead ſhall riſe againe, and that there ſhall bee a Reſurrection from the dead. But you ſayd it was a branch of happines unto
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:16967:83"/>the faithfull, that their bodyes roſe from death to life, how may this bee prooved?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>This alſo may be ſufficiently proved out of the Scripture, and that, by theſe 7 rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons alſo.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Becauſe it is ſaid that they <hi>are counted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Reſurrection: Luke</hi> 20, 35. Therefore the Reſurrection is a favour, &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a branch of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe unto them.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Becauſe they are called <hi>the children of the Reſurrection, Luk:</hi> 20: 36. and they are ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:16967:83"/>(as in other reſpects ſo in this) becauſe they riſe <hi>Gods children,</hi> (as they lived and dyed) &amp; are in his favor, which is a great happineſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe they are ſaid to be <hi>equall to the Angels,</hi> (when they are raiſed) <hi>Luke</hi> 20.36: and the Angels are happy, for nothing but happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe can befall them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, that if the faithfull did not riſe, they <hi>were of all men most miſerable,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15.19: therefore becauſe they doe riſe againe, they are happy.</p>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:16967:84"/>
               <p n="5">5. Becauſe when they are raiſed from death to life, they are called <hi>bleſſed:</hi> for Chriſt will call unto them, and ſay, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Matth:</hi> 25.34.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The reſurrection from the dead is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of happineſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as it hath beene ſaid before) the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralneſſe, weaknes, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and morrality of the body is aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and deſtroyed; and by the reſurrection, it is made a ſpirituall, ſtrong, incorruptible, and immortall body; yea it is raiſed a <hi>glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:16967:84"/>body,</hi> to be made fit to enter into and enjoy the glory of heaven, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15.41.50.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And laſtly, the reſurrection of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from death to life, is a degree of happines becauſe the aſſured ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of it did work in the faithfull, both more grace, and alſo more peace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.15, 16. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 16.9. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, I cannot deny, but theſe reaſons doe prove the point moſt cleerely: but one thing there is, that
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:16967:85"/>I am not as yet reſolved of, namely, I would faine learne, how the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from the dead ſhould be a happines to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, more than to the wicked and unfaithfull; for all both good and bad ariſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but all both good and bad, <hi>juſt and unjuſt, muſt ariſe from death to life, Iohn</hi> 5.28. <hi>Acts</hi> 24.15: but though this be true, yet there is a great difference in their riſing, and this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ſhewes the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of the one, and the unhappineſſe of the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="153" facs="tcp:16967:85"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein, I pray you, is the difference betwixt the reſurrection of the godly and of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It appeares ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in three things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All ariſe not the ſame manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, for ſome riſe <hi>juſt,</hi> and godly, as they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and dyed, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.14: yea they riſe <hi>Gods children, Luke</hi> 22.36: but others riſe <hi>unjust,</hi> unrighteous and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as they lived and dyed, <hi>Acts</hi> 24 15.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All ariſe not by the ſame meanes; for the godly ariſe by
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:16967:86"/>Chriſts mediation and reſurrection, as his members, 1 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 4.14. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.3, 4. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4.14. But the wicked ariſe from death to life onely by Gods power, and as his creatures.</p>
               <p n="3">3. All ariſe not to the ſame end, for the godly ariſe to the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of life,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall bleſſedneſſe, <hi>Ioh:</hi> 5.29. <hi>Matth:</hi> 25.32.34: <hi>To ſhine as the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the firmament,</hi> and <hi>as the ſtarres for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and ever, Dan.</hi> 12.2. Whereas the ungodly ariſe to the <hi>reſurrection of condemnation, Iohn</hi> 5.29:
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:16967:86"/>and to <hi>ſhame and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting contempt, Dan:</hi> 12.2.</p>
               <p>Some alſo have thought, that there is a fourth difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the juſt and unjuſt, (namely) that <hi>the dead in Christ ſhall ariſe</hi> before them that have dyed out of him: and for that they alledge a place in <hi>S. Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 4.16.</p>
               <p>But I anſwer, though it be not a thing impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that the godly ſhall ariſe before the wicked, yet doe I not thinke that that place
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:16967:87"/>proves it; becauſe that place ſpeakes not of an order betwixt the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the godly and wicked; but of an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der betwixt the dead in Chriſt, and the living in Chriſt at his ſecond comming: and that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is, that the dead in Chriſt ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, (or goe before unto heaven and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe) the living, or them that ſhall be alive at Chriſts ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But I pray you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not that degree of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, whereof both the ſoules and bodies of the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:16967:87"/>godly partake at the end of the world.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>This happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath 6 branches:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Both ſoule and body ſhall bee joyned together, even the <hi>very ſame, Iob</hi> 19.25, 26.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They ſhall bee freed from <hi>ever dying any more, Luke</hi> 20.36.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ſanctified with that meaſure of grace whereof a creature can be capable for the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of him to enjoy the heavenly glory, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15.49.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Being ſanctified, they ſhall be tranſlated
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:16967:88"/>and received into the kingdome of heaven, <hi>Matth:</hi> 25.34.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Being tranſlated, they ſhall partake of glory with God and Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.24.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Partaking of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly glory, they ſhall enjoy it <hi>for ever,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 4.17.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe indeede are excellent degrees of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, (the Lord fit us to partake of them.) but I pray you remember to ſhew mee the third gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall point neceſſary to be knowne in the doctrine of ſalvation; which was, the meanes whereby it is effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:16967:88"/>and brought to paſſe in the ſeverall degrees thereof.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I will,
<note place="margin">The means whereby ſaluation is effected.</note> (by the grace of God:) Theſe meanes are certaine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wrought by God, that bring to paſſe mans ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are actions that properly belong to the ſeverall Perſons of the ſacred Trinity, namely 1. God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; 2. God the Sonne; and 3. God the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What were the actions of God the Father, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:16967:89"/>mans ſalvation was ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Twofold: 1. In reſpect of Chriſt, his appointing and <hi>ſending him</hi> into the world to ſave it, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16: and his ſetting him in the office of his Mediator<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.28. <hi>Matth:</hi> 3.17. 2. And in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the faithfull, his juſtifying of them, his being reconciled unto them, and his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopting of them to be his children, and heires of heaven, whereof you have heard before in the degrees of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:16967:89"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What were the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of God the Sonne, which hee did to bring to paſſe our ſalvation?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They were thoſe, whereby hee merited and procured, that the Elect ſhould be ſurely brought into Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour againe, and ſafely carried to heaven; for he is called the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of our ſalvation, Hebr:</hi> 5.9: and the <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne of our ſalvation, Hehr:</hi> 2.10. And hee is called a <hi>Saviour,</hi> and <hi>our Saviour,</hi> 23 times in the New Teſtament. And theſe actions of Chriſt concerned ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:16967:90"/>1 his conception and birth: or 2. his life: or 3. his death: or 4. his reſurrection: or 5. aſcenſion: or 6. his ſitting on Gods right hand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What was Chriſts conception and birth, and the merit of them to our ſalvation?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſts concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and birth was his incarnation, whereby he tooke into the unity of his Perſon, (being the Sonne of God) the man then in framing in the wombe of the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> By this (being a great abaſing
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:16967:90"/>to him, <hi>Phil:</hi> 2.6, 7. <hi>Hebr:</hi> 2.14:) he merited and procured, that our originall ſinne, wherein we were conceived and borne of our parents, ſhould be pardoned and purged, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 51.3.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What were the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſts life, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee wrought our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They were theſe principally.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In his life hee was <hi>just</hi> &amp; righteous, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18: for hee <hi>knew no ſinne</hi> experimentally, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21: But was <hi>holy, and ſeparate from ſinners, Hebr:</hi> 7.26: <hi>Hee
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:16967:91"/>was Gods righteous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, Iſay</hi> 53.11: <hi>He was made unto us righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1.30: That by the imputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the merit thereof to all true beleevers, their imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect righteouſnes might be covered, and they therein accepted, and <hi>preſented</hi> as <hi>faultleſſe, Iude verſe</hi> 24: <hi>holy and without blame, Eph:</hi> 5.25: Yea that hee might <hi>establiſh them unblamea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in holines before God,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 3 13.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In his life, Chriſt made many heavenly prayers to God his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:16967:91"/>for his Elect; and by them Chriſt meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that their <hi>faith might not faile, Luke</hi> 22.32: nor they fall from grace; but be brought ſafe to glory in heaven, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.11.24.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the life of Chriſt 1. hee endured much poverty, <hi>Mat:</hi> 8.20: <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not a houſe to put his head in</hi> of his owne, though he were <hi>Lord of all, Acts</hi> 10.36. 2. Hee was much ſhamed and diſgraced, being <hi>revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and rayled upon, Mat:</hi> 27.30. And 3. he was put to much paine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>buffeted and ſcourged,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:16967:92"/>Matth:</hi> 27.26. <hi>Ioh:</hi> 19.1. <hi>Matth:</hi> 26.6, 7. But Chriſt merited and procured for us here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that by his <hi>povertie we might be made rich,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 8.9: that by his diſgrace wee might be honoured with this <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of being Gods children, Iohn</hi> 1.12: that <hi>by his ſtripes we might be healed,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2.24: And that all our afflictions might be ſanctified and ſeaſoned, to our refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What was Christs action at his death where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he merited our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:16967:92"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>He willingly <hi>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d downe his life,</hi> when (by his divine power) hee might have held it, and <hi>none could have taken it from him, Iohn</hi> 10.17. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16. Hereby Chriſt offered up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a propitiatory ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for the <hi>ranſome</hi> of mankind, <hi>Gal:</hi> 4.5. <hi>Heb:</hi> 10.6, 7, 8: and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee redeemed the Elect from the ſecond death, which is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and from the tyranny of the Divell, <hi>Hebr:</hi> 2.14. <hi>Iam:</hi> 5.20. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What was Christs
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:16967:93"/>reſurrection, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of it for our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſts reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was the freeing of himſelfe from the power of death, under which hee was held in the grave, ſome part of three dayes; and the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niting againe of his ſoule which was in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to his body which lay in the grave: Chriſt merited hereby, that the faithfull ſhould riſe againe from death to life, as members of his myſticall body, and be <hi>begotten to a lively hope</hi> of their owne reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:16967:93"/>by the power of his, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15.19, 20. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.3. 1 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 4.14.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What was Chriſts Aſcenſion, and what did he merit thereby, tending to our ſalvation?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſts Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was his leaving to live any longer on the earth as man, and his entring into heaven both in ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, there to continue till the end of the world, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.9, 10, 11. <hi>Hebr:</hi> 4.14. By Chriſts Aſcenſion into heaven, he tooke poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it for the
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:16967:94"/>faithfull, that at the end of their lives, he might <hi>receive</hi> their ſoules thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.59: and at the end of the world he might receive into it both their ſoules and bodies, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.2. <hi>Heb:</hi> 6.20.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What was Chriſts ſitting on the right hand of God the Father in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? and what did hee merit thereby for our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſts <hi>ſitting on the right hand</hi> of the Father in heaven, is his partaking (as man) of heavenly glory, farre above all creatures,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:16967:94"/>
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1.3. The merit thereof, is his <hi>Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> for us, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.24, 25: for in heaven hee continually <hi>appeares in Gods preſence for us, Heb:</hi> 9.24: to preſent all his merits unto God his Father, for our benefit; that God beholding the worth of them, hee might continually ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the vertue and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of them, to the converſion and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Elect, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively to the worlds end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now you have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mec, what were the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct ons of God the Father,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:16967:95"/>and God the Sonne, which they wrought for the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of mans ſalvation; I pray you alſo tell mee, what were the actions of the Holy Ghost for that end?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They were of two kindes:
<note place="margin">The acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit for ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting mans ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</note> 1. Such as he wrought in Chriſt, that was to be the Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the world: and 2. ſuch as hee wrought in them that are to bee ſaved by him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What were the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, wrought in Ieſus Chriſt by the Holy Ghoſt, for the bringing to paſſe of mans ſalvation?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They were three:
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:16967:95"/>1. the ſanctifying of the ſeede of the woman, for the framing of his body thereof, as hee was man, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.35. 2. The declaring of him to be the Saviour of the world, by <hi>deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon him like a dove, Matth:</hi> 3.16. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.33. 3. The filling of him with the gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Spirit <hi>above meaſure, Iohn</hi> 3.34: and <hi>above his fellowes, Hebr:</hi> 1.9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Holy Spirit, which he workes in them that are to bee ſaved, for the effecting thereof?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:16967:96"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are two. 1. Regeneration, or bringing them into the ſtate of grace. 2. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, or keeping them therein.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, I have heard much of Regeneration, but I doe not well underſtand it: I pray you therefore cauſe mee to understand better what it is?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Regeneration is an action of the holy Spirit,
<note place="margin">The Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit.</note> whereby Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are <hi>begotten again, borne againe;</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed,</hi> or made new a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.3: <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein doth the
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:16967:96"/>holy Spirit regenerate Chriſtians?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Not in making new the ſubſtance of their ſoules, nor in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing their ſoules with new parts, powers and faculties: But Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration conſiſts in healing and recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, rectifying and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending, purging and ſanctifying (with a new ſupply of grace) the former parts, powers and faculties, that were wholly depraved, and corrupted with ſinne, through <hi>Adams</hi> diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, <hi>Ecclefiaſt:</hi> 7.29.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="176" facs="tcp:16967:97"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>To what end doth the holy Spirit regenerate Chriſtians by his grace?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>For a twofold end, in reſpect of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>To enable them to ſerve God ſincerely and <hi>acceptably</hi> in this world, <hi>Hebr:</hi> 12.28: <hi>in newneſſe of ſpirit, Rom:</hi> 7.6: and in newneſſe of life, <hi>Rom:</hi> 6.4. For <hi>they are created</hi> (anew) <hi>in Christ Ieſus unto good workes, which God had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ordained that they ſhould walke in, Eph:</hi> 2.10. This they could not doe, as they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:16967:97"/>of their parents, for ſo they were <hi>begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in ſinne, Pſal:</hi> 51.5: and <hi>borne of, and after the fleſh, Iohn</hi> 3.3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29: <hi>which cannot pleaſe God, Rom:</hi> 8.8. And therefore to the end, they may bee fitly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and effectually enabled, to doe the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly duties of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, they muſt be made <hi>new men and women:</hi> for the image of God, which (through <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> ſinne) was defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in them, as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing right knowing, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and doing Gods will, muſt againe be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed</hi>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:16967:98"/>in them, <hi>Col:</hi> 3.10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the ſecond end, why the holy Spirit doth regenerate Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It is, to order them, and to ſet them in the way to heaven; which is, to make them <hi>meete partakers of that inheritance, Col:</hi> 1.12. For <hi>without holineſse no man ſhall ſee the Lord, Hebr.</hi> 12.14. Into the <hi>new Ieruſalem</hi> of heaven, ſhall in no wiſe <hi>enter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny uncleane thing, Revel.</hi> 21.27. And <hi>fleſh and blood cannot inherit the kingdome of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:16967:98"/>15.50. Now they can not goe to heaven as they are begotten of their naturall parents; for ſo they are the <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of diſobedience, Eph.</hi> 5.6: the <hi>children of wrath Eph:</hi> 2.3: and the <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Divell, Iohn</hi> 8.44. And therefore to the end they may be made capable of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they muſt by the holy Spirit <hi>bee turned from darkeneſſe to light, and from the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan unto God, that they may receive an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with them that are ſanctified, Acts</hi> 26.18, 19. For holineſſe is the
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:16967:99"/>way to happineſſe, and grace unto glory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But by what meanes doth the holy Spirit rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate Chriſtians, and make them new?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>By the incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible ſeede of <hi>the word of truth, Iam:</hi> 1.18: which is <hi>the word of God:</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. which is <hi>the Goſpell,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. which is <hi>the Preaching of Ieſus Chriſt: Rom.</hi> 16.25: and <hi>of ſalvation: Act.</hi> 13.26. In whom they are <hi>begotten againe:</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. and <hi>created</hi> anew: <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ought care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:16967:99"/>to attend upon this ordinance, which is <hi>the power of God to ſalvation to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve: Rom.</hi> 1.16.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I pray you Sir, What is Preſervation, which, you ſaid, was the ſecond act on of the holy Spirit, which he workes, to bring to paſſe mans ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Preſervation,
<note place="margin">The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</note> is an action of the holy Spirit, whereby he up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth them that are regenerate, that they fall not away from grace, but be kept to continue therein.</p>
               <p>That the regenerate
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:16967:100"/>are kept in the ſtate of grace, is plaine by <hi>S. Peter;</hi> who ſaith, that they are <hi>kept unto ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.3.5. And that they doe <hi>receive the end of their faith, which is the ſalvation of their ſoules,</hi> verſe 9. And that they are kept thereunto by the <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> is as plaine by the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, where he ſaith, they are <hi>kept by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.5: which is the <hi>power of the holy Ghoſt, Rom:</hi> 15.13. For they are <hi>led by the Spirit, Gal:</hi> 5.18: They <hi>walke in the Spirit, Gal:</hi> 5.16. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.14.
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:16967:100"/>They <hi>live in the Spirit, Gal:</hi> 5.25: They are <hi>ſealed by the Spirit, Eph:</hi> 1.13: <hi>ſtrengthened by the Spirit in the inner man, Eph:</hi> 3.16: And they are <hi>ſanctifyed by the Spirit wholly, and preſerved blameleſſe unto the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our Lord Ieſus Christ,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 5.23. 2 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 2.13. And if the regenerate bee kept by the holy Spirit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſalvation, then (in reſpect of Gods keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) can they not fall from grace, to miſſe ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the event &amp; end</p>
               <p>I know the ſtrongeſt Chriſtian is not able to
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:16967:101"/>ſtand of himſelfe, for even <hi>hee that ſtandeth must take heede leſt hee fall,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 10.12: And therefore <hi>hee muſt not be high-minded, but feare, Rom:</hi> 11.20.</p>
               <p>I acknowledge alſo, that there is nothing in grace it ſelfe, (as it is mans) but that it might faile; for it is received but <hi>in part</hi> in this life, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 13.9. And that which is but in part, is imperfect; and that which is imperfect, may (of it ſelfe) faile. Neither is there any thing in the particular grace of faith, but that
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:16967:101"/>it might faile too; for <hi>Peters</hi> faith might have <hi>failed,</hi> if Chriſt had not <hi>prayed that it might not faile, Luke</hi> 22.32: (and <hi>Peters</hi> faith was the ſame, (for nature and kinde) with the faith of all that are regenerate.) But though both theſe be true, both of grace generally, and of faith particularly; yet for all this the truely rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate do not fall from grace; but are preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved therein: for firſt, touching grace in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, I ſay, that it failes not; for it is <hi>the anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting which they receive,</hi>
                  <pb n="188" facs="tcp:16967:102"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="189" facs="tcp:16967:102"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="186" facs="tcp:16967:103"/>and <hi>which abides in them</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.27: and that which abides, failes not: for by it they are <hi>ſtrengthened and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to Gods heavenly kingdome,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.18. Secondly, touching the particular grace of faith, I ſay, that that failes not neither: 1. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt <hi>prayed</hi> not onely for <hi>Peters</hi> faith, <hi>that it might not faile;</hi> but for the faith of all the Elect and Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, that theirs might not faile; for he prayed that they might all <hi>bee kept by the Father in his Name,</hi> that <hi>they may bee
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:16967:103"/>one in God, as the Father and the Sonne are one, Iohn</hi> 17.11.15.20, 21: And Chriſt was heard and anſwered in all his prayers, <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.42. 2. The faith of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate failes not in the end, becauſe they are <hi>kept by the power of God through faith,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.5. Now if they bee kept <hi>through faith,</hi> then muſt they keepe the faith, and be kept in it alſo, elſe they cannot attaine ſalvation in the end: for if the regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate doe <hi>receive the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their ſoules as the end of their faith,</hi>
                  <pb n="188" facs="tcp:16967:104"/>1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.9: then muſt they by ſome meanes keepe their faith to the end.</p>
               <p>I know and confeſſe, that there bee many which thinke of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they have indeede the true faith and grace, (and ſo are thought by others to have it) when indeede they have it not; and theſe (after a ſort) may be thought to fall from faith and grace, becauſe in time they diſcover their hollowneſſe; for their <hi>faith workes not by love, Gal:</hi> 5.6: nor their <hi>love by obedience, Iohn</hi>
                  <pb n="189" facs="tcp:16967:104"/>14.15: Nor is their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience a ſincere en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to keepe all Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, <hi>Iam:</hi> 2.10. But this can not be called truely fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from grace; (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had not grace indeed, and they cannot fall from that they had not:) but from the profeſſion of grace and faith. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for all this, they that have true grace, doe by Gods power keepe it, and perſevere in it; for <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>fight a good fight, he finiſhed his courſe, and kept the faith,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6. <hi>They doe not
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:16967:105"/>withdraw themſelues, but beleeve to the ſalvation of their ſoules: Heb,</hi> 10, 28: therefore they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve to the end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mee th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nkes you prove this poynt ſo direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the word, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell what to ſay to the contrary: but there bee many learned men of a contrary mind, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I pray prove it unto me by ſome reaſon alſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I will, and it ſhall be by this which ſhall include diverſe branches.</p>
               <p>If the regenerate be not preſerved by God in the ſtate of grace, ſo
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:16967:105"/>as they ſhall certainely bee ſaved in the end, then it is either, 1 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God cannot keep them, or 2 becauſe he will, not keepe them; or 3 becauſe they haue no neede of his keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: or 4 Becauſe God thinks it beſt, to leaue every man to himſelfe, to keepe himſelfe; and to the uſe and choice of his owne freewill, to perſevere in grace, and faith, or to fall from it.</p>
               <p>But neither of theſe are true, as ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:16967:106"/>
               <p>Therefore the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate are preſerved by God, in the State of grace unto the end.</p>
               <p>Theſe foure particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, on which the truth of this argument doth ſtand; ſhall all be proved in order.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That God is able to keep the regenerate in the ſtate of grace, is plaine by <hi>Paul</hi> who ſaith, that <hi>God was able to keep that which he had committed unto him:</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12: By the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Iude,</hi> who ſaith that <hi>God is able to keepe them from falling: Iude v.</hi> 24. And no marvell ſeeing
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:16967:106"/>they are in <hi>his Fathers hands and in his,</hi> Chriſt ſaith <hi>none is able to pluck them out of his, or his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hands, Iohn.</hi> 10.28 29: and therefore <hi>they ſhall never periſh,</hi> ibid.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That God is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to keepe the truly Regenerate that haue grace indeede, is as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident by Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>that God ſhall confirme them unto the end,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4.8.9. <hi>He that had begun a good worke in them, will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it untill the day of Chriſt: Philipp.</hi> 1.6. and God is faithfull, <hi>who ſhall ſtabliſh them
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:16967:107"/>and keep them from evill,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 3.3: and <hi>Paul</hi> affirmes, that <hi>God would preſerve him to his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly kingdome,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.18.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate had neede to bee kept by God, in the ſtate of grace, will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be proved, if wee conſider, 1. that their corrupt nature, and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity</hi> (a fruit of it) are not quite ſubdued in them as long as they live, <hi>Rom:</hi> 7.17, 18. <hi>Heb:</hi> 3.12. 2. That grace is but imperfectly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in this life, as hath been ſhewed even now.
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:16967:107"/>3. That Sathan ſeekes to <hi>winnow</hi> them, that <hi>their faith might faile, Luke</hi> 22.32. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they are ſubject to many afflictions and perſecutions, which make many <hi>fall away, Matth:</hi> 13.21. <hi>Luke</hi> 8.13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That God doth not thinke it beſt to leave every man to himſelfe, to keepe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to the uſe and choice of his owne freewill, to perſevere in grace and faith, or to fall from it, ſhall bee prooved by two Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="196" facs="tcp:16967:108"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>If man were left by God to the uſe and choiſe of his owne free will to keepe himſelfe, and to perſevere in grace, or fall from it, then would theſe two great miſchiefes follow thereupon: 1. that then not God, but man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſhould make the difference betwixt him that perſeveres, and him that fals away. But this is denyed by <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>It is not in him that willeth, nor in him that runneth, but in God that ſhewes mercie, Rom:</hi> 9.16. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:16967:108"/>
                  <hi>Who maketh thee to differ from another, and what haſt thou, that thou hast not received?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4.7. 2. This miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief will follow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon alſo, that not God, but man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe muſt have the chiefe praiſe of his owne ſalvation. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed God might have ſome thankes: 1. for appointing and ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Saviour into the world: 2. for offering grace and ſalvation to man by him: and 3. for moving him by his Spirit to beleeve in Chriſt, that hee may
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:16967:109"/>be ſaved. But that hee doth indeede actually conſent to the motion of grace and receive it, doth indeed beleeve in Chriſt, and actually perſevere in grace: ſo as to be ſaved in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, this proceedes from himſelfe meerely, and onely from the good uſe and choiſe of his own freewill, when God left him to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to beleeve or not beleeve, and to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere or not perſevere: and therefore himſelfe muſt have the chiefe praiſe of his being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and not God, who
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:16967:109"/>of right is to have all the glory, of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, proceeding, and accompliſhing of the worke of our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I pray you giue me alſo the ſecond reaſon, why God thinks it not beſt, to leave every man to himſelfe, to perſevere or fall from grace.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>If every man were a like left to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to the uſe &amp; choice of his owne free-will, to perſevere or not perſevere, and none were actually kept unto ſalvation, nor ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually cauſed by the
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:16967:110"/>holy Spirit to perſevere in grace to the end, ſo that in the event they might certainly be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, then were it uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, whether any man ſhould in the event be ſaved or no; (for it is uncertaine in reſpect of the event, whether any man ſhould perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in the faith or no, becauſe it is uncerteine whether any man ſhold well uſe his freewill to perſevere or no:) and if it were uncertaine, whether any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold be ſaved or no in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, then were it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, whether the
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:16967:110"/>blood of Chriſt ſhedd on the Croſſe for mans ſalvation, ſhould bee ſpilt in vayne or no. For ſalvation is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by <hi>Christs bloud</hi> onely, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it there is no remisſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Heb.</hi> 9.14.22. And they onely that <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere</hi> in the faith ſhall be ſaved: <hi>Mat:</hi> 10.22. <hi>Reve:</hi> 2.10. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Regenerate are preſerved in the ſtate of grace by the holy Spirit, to the end, that Chriſt may not die in vayne, nor the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Regenerate be uncertaine, nor the
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:16967:111"/>chiefe prayſe of their ſalvation redound to themſelves, but to God onely and wholly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir I thanke you, I am fully ſatisfied in this poynt: you haue ſayd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, touching the first point of ſeeking to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; which was ſeeking to know the chiefe points of the doctrine of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: The last branch whereof was, the meanes whereby mans ſalvation is effected. I pray you now proceede to the ſecond point,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seeking to be affected with ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</note> 
                  <hi>which is,</hi> ſeeking to be affected with ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>That you may be
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:16967:111"/>moved to deſire to be ſaved, and to affect it, you muſt conſider theſe foure things chiefly: 1. the poſſibility of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it: 2. the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of getting it: 3. the excellency of it, when it is had and enjoyed: and 4. the certainty of holding it when wee have it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that it is poſsible for us to bee ſaved, if wee ſeeke it?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>By theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, offered, and promiſed in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:16967:112"/>
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 1.77. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.31, 32. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.23. <hi>Rom:</hi> 10.10.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe it is me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited and procured by Ieſus Chriſt, who hath done and ſuffered all things needfull for the purchaſing of it, <hi>Eph:</hi> 1.14. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.18, 19. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 6.20.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe ſalvation is already poſſeſſed and enjoyed, by infinite millions of Chriſtians, who have ſought and obtained it, <hi>Hebr:</hi> 11.3.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.1. <hi>Luke</hi> 23.42, 43. <hi>Matth:</hi> 11.12.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="205" facs="tcp:16967:112"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity of ſalvation ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>By theſe three reaſons alſo.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God which bids us ſeeke it; and by the threatning of the word, which denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth judgement to them that neglect to ſeeke it; wherof you have heard more particularly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By the words of our Saviour, who (ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of taking the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent opportunity of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelfe preach the Goſpell of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:16967:113"/>ſaith, <hi>One thing is neceſſary, Luke</hi> 10.42.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By conſidering and laying to heart the <hi>miſerable</hi> eſtate of not being ſaved, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15.18, 19. For <hi>it had beene better for them they had never beene borne, Matth:</hi> 26.24. And no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, ſeeing the Lord will one day pronounce that direfull ſentence, <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Divell and his Angels, Matth:</hi> 25.41.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of ſalvation bee ſhewed?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="207" facs="tcp:16967:113"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>By theſe foure things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The excellency of Gods love, and free grace, which is the foundation of it, and which moved God to appoint and provide it, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.1. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.18, 19. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The excellencie of the price by which it was purchaſed and procured for us, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſt <hi>himſelfe, Gal:</hi> 1.4. <hi>Eph:</hi> 1.24. <hi>His life,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16. <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.10: <hi>His blood, Acts</hi> 20.28. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.23: <hi>His death, Hebr:</hi> 2.10: Yea <hi>a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed death on the Croſſe,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:16967:114"/>Phil:</hi> 2.8. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The excellency of the nature and parts, degrees and priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, benefits and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of our ſalvation, wherof you have heard at large before in the two firſt points.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The excellency of the perſons, that in the event are to bee made partakers of it, namely the <hi>Elect,</hi> and the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the Lord, 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.10. <hi>Tit:</hi> 1.1: To whom the very Elect Angels are <hi>miniſtring ſpirits,</hi> to attend upon them, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1.14.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I pray you how may
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:16967:114"/>the certaintie of ſalvation be proved?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>By three things.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The Decree and purpoſe of God to ſave true beleevers in <hi>Chriſt Eph,</hi> 1.5.9. which <hi>stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſure:</hi> 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.19. and cannot be changed, becauſe <hi>with God there is no variableneſſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhadow of turning: Iam:</hi> 1:17.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The prom ſe, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and oath of God, to ſave them that are in Chriſt: <hi>Luke</hi> 1.72.73. all which are <hi>immutable: Heb:</hi> 6.17.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The power and goodnes, righteouſnes,
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:16967:115"/>&amp; faithfulnes of God, in performing the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of ſalvation to them to whom it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, and is intended: <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.21. <hi>Heb,</hi> 11.19. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh good Sir: it may bee, that ſalvation may in it ſelfe, and in the event be ſure to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but may they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves be ſure of it?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, they they may, (being truely faithfull) at one time or other, before they dye, &amp; in one meaſure or other of aſſurance, (namely, ſuch as ſhall be ſutable to their tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls,
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:16967:115"/>and ſufficient to comfort them in their afflictions, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1.5:) but all have not like aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of ſalvation; neither hath any one the like aſſurance al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, nor in the ſame degree, free from doubting.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>By theſe two reaſons:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed to their ſpirit by Gods Spirit, (who ſhedds Gods love abroad in their hearts, Rom: 5.5:) that they are Gods children;</hi> and conſequently that
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:16967:116"/>they ſhall be ſaved: for none are ſaved but onely Gods children, <hi>Romans</hi> 8.16: And they may bee ſure of that which Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit doth witneſſe unto them, becauſe he is <hi>the Spirit of truth,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh:</hi> 5.6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers in Chriſt are <hi>ſealed with the Spirit of promiſe;</hi> and <hi>receive an earneſt of their inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Eph:</hi> 1.13, 14. Now an <hi>earneſt penny,</hi> it gives aſſurance of the bargain, and a <hi>ſeale</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes &amp; aſſures a wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to which it is put.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:16967:116"/>were aſſured of it; for <hi>Paul</hi> was <hi>perſwaded &amp; aſſured, that nothing ſhould ſeparate them from the love of God in Chriſt, Rom:</hi> 8, 38. &amp; <hi>Iohn knew the love of God to him,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh:</hi> 4.16. &amp; 5.19. Now the Apoſtles had not this perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or aſſurance as they were Apoſtles, but as they were Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, becauſe they were not ſaved as Apoſtles, but as Chriſtians.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh, but how can they be ſure to be ſaved, when they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſure to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere to the end? for they onely are ſaved that perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere to the end.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="214" facs="tcp:16967:117"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They that onely profeſſe to have grace and faith in Chriſt, (but have it not indeed) can never be ſure to bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee ſure to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, for they cannot perſevere in that which they have not: But (for all this) they that have grace indeed, and are truely regenerate, may be ſure to perſevere: 1. becauſe God loves the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to whom hee gives ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 13.13: And whom hee loves once, <hi>hee loves to the end, Iohn</hi> 13.1. And therefore they perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:16967:117"/>in grace to the end, that they may be loved in the end: and therefore are they lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the end, that they may perſevere to the end. <hi>Iohn</hi> 13.1. 2 They may bee ſure to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, becauſe the Lord hath promiſed that <hi>the peace of God ſhall keepe their hearts and mindes in Ieſus Christ: Phil:</hi> 4.7, 3 They may be ſure to perſevere, becauſe the Spirit of God ſo aſſiſts them: that by the motion and efficacy thereof, they (that are truely &amp; indeed borne of God and begotten
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:16967:118"/>of him, and not Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally onely) <hi>they doe keepe themſelves, and that wicked one toucheth them not:</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.18. For they <hi>building up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their moſt holy faith,</hi> and praying <hi>in the holy Ghoſt</hi> for continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all aſſiſtance, <hi>they keepe themſelves in the loue of God, looking for the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of our Lord Ieſus Christ unto eternall life: Iude v</hi> 20.21. 4 They may bee ſure to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in grace, <hi>if the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynting which they have received abide in them;</hi> and <hi>if his ſeede remaine in them:</hi> and this hath
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:16967:118"/>God promiſed to the truly regenerate, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.27. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.9. For though in reſpect of ſome things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, (whereof you have heard in the point of Preſervation by the Spirit) and as of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they could not perſevere, nor be ſure to perſevere, but fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; yet in other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects they doe, as hath beene ſhewed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, I am much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to you for your great paines in the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me the ſecond point of ſeeking to be ſaved; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n all the branches there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of:
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:16967:119"/>I pray you now in the laſt place ſhew me the laſt point, which is,</hi> ſeeking to get ſalvation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt get ſalvation,
<note place="margin">Seeking to get ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</note> by perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſome actions, which God requires, on your part to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, for the attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Me thinks it ſeemes ſtrange to mee, how man can get and attaine ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by any action of his, which he doth himſelfe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>When I ſpeake of ſome actions of men whereby they attaine unto ſalvation, I would have you to conſider two things:</p>
               <pb n="219" facs="tcp:16967:119"/>
               <p n="1">1. That I doe not meane that man doth theſe actions, by any abſolute activity or ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency that is in, and of himſelfe, or the power and dominion hee hath over his owne will: for he doth them by Gods will, and by his effectuall grace, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing and enabling him thereunto, who <hi>workes in him to will and to doe of his owne good pleaſure, Phil:</hi> 2.13. But I meane that theſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are done by their own underſtanding and will; (for they are not ignorant of what they
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:16967:120"/>doe, nor are they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to the doing of them.) Mans ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and godly acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are Gods, as hee moves him thereunto by his grace, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures him actually to conſent to the motion of grace: but they are mans owne actions, as hee is the next and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate doer of them; and as they proceede from him, as a vitall, and reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And therefore it is ſaid, that <hi>the juſt ſhall live by faith, Hab:</hi> 2.4. And therefore the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of beleeving are
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:16967:120"/>applyed to men in all the three perſons: <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, Acts</hi> 8.37: <hi>Thou beleeveſt, Rom:</hi> 10.9: <hi>Hee beleeves, Marke</hi> 16.16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When I ſay, man gets and attaines unto ſalvation by ſome acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his owne, I doe not meane, that there is any merit or worth, in theſe his actions to procure or deſerve ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, in the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or degree as they come from man: But that God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch actions of men to bee conditions to bee performed on their part to make their
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:16967:121"/>perſons capable of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and that theſe actions have this effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy to this end, not as they be done by them, but as they are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God for them; and as he enables them to doe them according to his appointment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, I am fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied: But I pray you, what bee thoſe actions of men appointed by God, as conditions on their part to bee performed for the attaining of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They bee of three kindes, whereof the firſt prepare them
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:16967:121"/>to get it: the ſecond give them title and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to claime it, and receive it: and the third give them aſſurance of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What be the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that prepare them to get ſalvation?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are theſe:</p>
               <p>Firſt, they muſt know and acknowledg their ſinne and miſery, they muſt beleeve and feele the guilt and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of their ſins, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. For this will make them to feele their <hi>neede</hi> of ſalvation, and their unability to ſave themſelves: <hi>Mat:</hi>
                  <pb n="224" facs="tcp:16967:122"/>9.13: and that they <hi>neede to repent,</hi> and cry God mercy, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.9: And this is wrought by the preaching of the law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They muſt alſo beleeve the Goſpell, (that is) conſent in their opinion &amp; judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that there is ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to be had; and that this is a truth of God, that it is poſſible for men to get ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and this is wrought by the Goſpell, <hi>Marke</hi> 1.15. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.4.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They muſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily be ſorry for their
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:16967:122"/>paſt ſinnes, and unfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly purpoſe to leave them, (which is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance begun in the roote) <hi>Matth:</hi> 21.32.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They muſt hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and earneſtly deſire to be ſaved, <hi>Matth:</hi> 5.6. <hi>Iſay</hi> 55.1.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult what to doe, and enquire further into and after the way and the meanes of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, with a minde to follow thoſe dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions accordingly, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.30: And theſe three laſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are wrought by the Law and Goſpell,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:16967:123"/>whereby they are both drawne and driven to ſeeke and get ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P,</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What be the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, which give them title and intereſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſalvation: to claime and receive it of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Actions that g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue title to claime and receiue ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</note> They are belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving or truſting <hi>in Ieſus Christ: Rom,</hi> 10: 9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1:13. whereby <hi>weary and heavy laden</hi> ſinners <hi>come to</hi> Chriſt for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>Math:</hi> 11, 28. <hi>Iohn</hi> 6, 35: and reſt onely upon the merits of the righteouſnes of his life and death, for ſalvation in all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:16967:123"/>degrees thereof. For by this faith, they get and lay hold upon the Saviour himſelfe, even the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and are <hi>engraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed</hi> and united to him: <hi>Rom,</hi> 11: 19.20. for by faith, <hi>Christ is in</hi> true beleevers, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 13, 5. <hi>he liues in them: Gal:</hi> 2 20 and <hi>dwells in them: Eph.</hi> 3.17.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What reaſons may be brought from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture to prooue this which you ſay, concerning the action of</hi> beleeving in Chriſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe:</p>
               <p n="1">1 Beleeving in <hi>Chriſt</hi>
                  <pb n="228" facs="tcp:16967:124"/>is the action appointed by God, to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by man for recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſalvation, becauſe it is requyred of him as the condition to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>forgivenes of ſinnes Act,</hi> 10, 43. reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and <hi>peace</hi> with God: <hi>Rom:</hi> 5, 1. &amp; 3:25. <hi>justification: Act:</hi> 13, 29. <hi>adoption: Iohn</hi> 1.12. <hi>bleſſednes, Gal.</hi> 3, 9: <hi>eternall life: Iohn</hi> 3, 16. <hi>eaſe</hi> from the burden of ſinne: <hi>Matth:</hi> 11, 28. <hi>quenching all Satans fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry darts, Eph:</hi> 6, 16. not being <hi>confounded of our ſinnes: Rom.</hi> 10.11. and of <hi>pleaſing God: Heb.</hi> 11.6.</p>
               <pb n="229" facs="tcp:16967:124"/>
               <p n="2">2 Beleeving in Chriſt is the action requyred by God, to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on mans part for receiving ſalvation; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by this meanes, ſalvation comes to him by the <hi>free grace</hi> and mercy, loue &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God: <hi>Rom,</hi> 4: 16. <hi>Eph,</hi> 2, 8.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Beleeving in <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the action and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion required on mans part, for obtaining ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; becauſe hereby the <hi>promiſe</hi> of ſalvation will be <hi>ſure</hi> to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.16: which by the action of obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Law it could
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:16967:125"/>not bee, becauſe hee could not performe it, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.39. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.3.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Beleeving in Chriſt is the action and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition required, to be performed by man, for the getting of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; becauſe it makes a man renounce his own righteouſneſſe, and to goe out of himſelfe to another for it, (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) to Ieſus Chriſt, to be ſaved by his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, <hi>Matth:</hi> 11.28. <hi>Ioh:</hi> 6.35. <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.9. <hi>Gal:</hi> 2.19.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which Chriſtians
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:16967:125"/>muſt performe to make their ſalvation ſure unto themſelves?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers:
<note place="margin">Actions that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> for they concerne either 1. God, or 2. our brethren; or 3. our ſelves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What actions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are ſuch as belong either 1. to God the Father; or 2. to God the Sonne: or 3. to God the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What actions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to God the Father?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are three principally.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Fearing</hi> to offend
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:16967:126"/>God, and caring to pleaſe him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 7.32: For unto ſuch, and for their comfort is <hi>the word of ſalvation ſent, Acts</hi> 13.26: and ſuch may <hi>worke out their ſalvation,</hi> (that is) the aſſuming (not the procuring of it) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelves, <hi>Phil:</hi> 2.12. And no marvell, ſeeing <hi>Gods mercy is on them that feare him for ever, Luke</hi> 1.50. Such <hi>know that they are redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the precious blood of Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.17, 18: and ſuch are <hi>bleſſed, Pſal:</hi> 128.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Loving</hi> God, and
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:16967:126"/>ſetting our hearts and delight upon him; for ſuch may <hi>know that they are of the truth,</hi> and <hi>ſhall aſſure their hearts before him,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.18, 19: And that <hi>they may have boldneſſe in the day of judgement,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.16, 17. And no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, ſeeing their love to God will <hi>aſſure them that they are borne of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.7: that <hi>they dwell in God, and God in them,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.19: that <hi>they are knowne</hi> and <hi>acknowledged,</hi> and <hi>approoved of God:</hi> The firſt to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the 8 chapter, 3 verſe:
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:16967:127"/>that <hi>all things ſhall worke to their good,</hi> (that is) to the furtherance of their ſanctification and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28: And that the <hi>crowne of life</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, and the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of <hi>the kingdome of heaven is promiſed to ſuch as love God, Iam:</hi> 1.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Chriſtians muſt <hi>hope</hi> in God, (that is) aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly expect &amp; looke for, yea patiently abide and waite for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of all Gods promiſes, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that of the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the body, and of eternall life; for they
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:16967:127"/>are <hi>ſaved by hope, Rom.</hi> 8.24: And <hi>Hope is a hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met of ſalvation</hi> to them, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.8: And <hi>an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker to the ſoule both ſure and ſtedfaſt, and which entreth into heaven, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the forerunner is for us entred, even Ieſus, Heb:</hi> 6.19, 20. And no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, ſeeing their <hi>hope</hi> will not deceive, <hi>nor make them aſhamed, Rom:</hi> 5.5: Becauſe into the hearts of ſuch as hope in God, <hi>the love of God is ſhed abroad by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost, Rom:</hi> 5.5: And <hi>they rejoyce in the hope of the glory of God, Rom:</hi> 5.3.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="236" facs="tcp:16967:128"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What actions of Chriſtians concerne Ieſus Christ, that will aſſure them of their ſalvation?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are theſe two principally.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They muſt obey him in all his Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call precepts and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, which belong to the hearing and beleeving of the Goſpell preached; and to the adminiſtring and receiving the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>in remembrance of him, Matth:</hi> 28.20. <hi>Marke</hi> 1.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.16. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.26, 27. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 11.24, 25. For unto ſuch as <hi>obey</hi> him
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:16967:128"/>herein, Ieſus Chriſt is <hi>become author of eternall ſalvation: Heb:</hi> 5.9. &amp; no marvell, ſeeing they are <hi>bleſſed</hi> of God: <hi>Luk</hi> 11.28. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.3. they <hi>are of</hi> God (that is) cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen &amp; beloved of him: <hi>Iohn 8, 4.7.</hi> and they are <hi>the ſheepe of Christ,</hi> to whome <hi>hee will give e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life: Iohn</hi> 10:27.28.</p>
               <p n="2">2 They muſt <hi>love</hi> &amp; <hi>long for, looke</hi> and <hi>waite</hi> for, the ſecond <hi>appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or coming of Chriſt.</hi> For ſuch beleeve that <hi>there is layd up for them a crowne of righteouſnes, which the Lord the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:16967:129"/>judge ſhall give them at that day:</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Titus:</hi> 2.13.14. Such the Lord Chriſt <hi>will deliver from the wrath to come:</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.10: and to ſuch <hi>he will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare the ſecond time un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſalvation: Hebr.</hi> 9.28.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What actions of Christians concerne the holy Spirit, that will aſſure them of ſalvation?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe. Not to <hi>reſist,</hi> or <hi>vexe the holy Spirit: Act,</hi> 7, 51. <hi>Iſai</hi> 63.10. not to <hi>quench or grieve it:</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30: but to be <hi>led</hi> thereby, and to
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:16967:129"/>
                  <hi>walke</hi> after the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and guidance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; for ſuch <hi>are ſealed to the day of Redemption, Eph:</hi> 4.30. <hi>They are Gods children: Rom.</hi> 8.14. and unto ſuch <hi>there is no condemnation, for they are in Chriſt Ieſus: Rom.</hi> 8.1: and in them <hi>the righteouſnes of the Law is fulfilled: Rom.</hi> 8.4: (namely) ſincerely, &amp; in Gods favorable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What actions that concerne our neighbour, must Christians doe to aſſure them of ſalvation?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Loving him; which is manifeſted,
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:16967:130"/>chiefely in <hi>giving, Heb.</hi> 13, 16. and 9, 10. and forgiving: <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.32. &amp; is exerciſed toward all men, but ſpecially toward <hi>the houſhold of faith, and all ſincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians: Gal.</hi> 6: 10. For theſe loving affections and actions <hi>accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſalvation; Heb:</hi> 6, 9. and they which are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed therein with <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence unto the end,</hi> doe attaine <hi>the full aſſurance of hope: Heb,</hi> 6.11. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Chriſtians that love <hi>in deed</hi> and <hi>in truth,</hi> doe know <hi>that they are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated from death to life:</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.14: <hi>and that
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:16967:130"/>they are of the truth, and ſhall aſſure their heartes before God:</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.19. and unto ſuch God wil one day ſay, <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the kingdome prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the beginning of the world; becauſe when I was hungry yee fed mee, when I was naked yee clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed me, and when I was ſicke and in priſon ye vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited me</hi> in my members <hi>Math.</hi> 25.34.35.36.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What actions bee they, that concerne our ſelves, the doing whereof will aſſure us of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>They are theſe
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:16967:131"/>Nyne chiefely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Daily repenting of our daily ſinnes, with purpoſe and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of amendment, and crying God mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in Chriſt. For ſuch <hi>godly ſorrow for ſinne cauſing amendment,</hi> is <hi>unto ſalvation:</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7 10. <hi>Such departing from iniquitie,</hi> is a ſeale un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, that the <hi>Lord knoweth they are his,</hi> &amp; belong unto him. 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 2, 19: and ſuch purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of themſelves from ſinne, is an aſſurance unto them, that they are <hi>veſſels of honour:</hi> 2.
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:16967:131"/>2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.21: and veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of honour are <hi>veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells of mercy, prepared unto glory, Rom:</hi> 9.23.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Giving and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrating our ſelves to the <hi>ſervice of God with an upright heart,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron:</hi> 28.9. For ſuch <hi>prove what is that good, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, and perfect will of God, Rom:</hi> 12.1: that is, they underſtand thereby that it is Gods will and purpoſe to ſave them: and no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, ſeeing <hi>Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> have the <hi>fruit</hi> of their ſervice <hi>in holineſſe</hi>
                  <pb n="244" facs="tcp:16967:132"/>here, and the <hi>end eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life hereafter, Rom:</hi> 6.19.22.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mortifying</hi> the old man, (that is) ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing and weakening the power of our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature by the word, prayer, and faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and by <hi>denying</hi> to our ſelves the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and opportunities of ſinne; ſpecially of thoſe ſinnes to which wee are moſt inclined by nature or cuſtome, <hi>Col:</hi> 3.5: For <hi>ſuch ſhall live</hi> in heaven, <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.13: ſuch may with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing <hi>looke for that
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:16967:132"/>bleſſed hope, and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious appearing of that great God, and of our Saviour Ieſus Christ, Tit:</hi> 2.12.13: And no marvell, ſeeing ſuch are <hi>Chriſts,</hi> and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of him, <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.24.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which is the fourth?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Strengthening the <hi>new man,</hi> or the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner man</hi> by the word, prayer, and Sacraments, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4.16. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2.2: And thereby growing in the number &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their Chriſtian vertues and graces; for thereby they ſhall <hi>make their calling and election
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:16967:133"/>ſure;</hi> and <hi>an entrance ſhall bee miniſtred unto them abundantly into the everlaſting Kingdome of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Christ,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet:</hi> 5. to 12. And ſuch <hi>ſhall bee able to comprehend with all Saints, what is the breadth, and length, and depth and height of the love of God toward them in Ieſus Christ, Eph:</hi> 3.16.18: Yea <hi>God will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh their hearts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable in holineſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God even the Father, at the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt with all Saints,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 3.12, 13.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="247" facs="tcp:16967:133"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which is the fifth?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Moderating our deſires to the pleaſures, profits and honours of this world, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 7.29, 30, 31: and ſetting our affections upon holy and heavenly things, <hi>Col:</hi> 3.1. For ſuch have their <hi>converſation in heaven,</hi> and that their <hi>end</hi> is ſalvation, <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.19, 20: Yea it is a ſigne, that ſuch as be thus <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 5.5.8: and are not beſotted and drunke with the things of this life, they have not their <hi>portion</hi> in this life, as the wicked have, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 17.14: but that
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:16967:134"/>God hath <hi>appointed them to obtaine ſalvation by our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſs:</hi> 5.8, 9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which is the ſixth?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Profeſſing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, the Goſpell and godlineſſe before men, zealouſly and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, diſcreetly, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly, <hi>Rom:</hi> 14.11: For Chriſt will <hi>confeſſe,</hi> and <hi>acknowledge</hi> ſuch <hi>before the Angels of God, Luke</hi> 12.8: ſuch <hi>lay hold on eternall life,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 6.12: Yea ſuch <hi>confeſſe unto ſalvation,</hi> and <hi>ſhall bee ſaved, Rom:</hi> 10.9, 10.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="249" facs="tcp:16967:134"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Getting and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping a good conſcience, being <hi>in all things deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> and endeavorous to pleaſe God, <hi>Hebr:</hi> 13.18. <hi>Acts</hi> 23.1. For ſuch may <hi>draw neere un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God with full aſſurance of faith, Hebr:</hi> 10.22: ſuch have <hi>hope toward God</hi> of a ioyfull <hi>reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> to eternall life, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.15, 16: and may have <hi>conſidence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God,</hi> and <hi>aſſure their hearts before him,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19 21.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which is the eighth?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Striving and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoring to perſevere in right beleeving, well
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:16967:135"/>doing, and patient ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15.1. <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.1 <hi>Hebr:</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.22. For ſuch ſhall <hi>be ſaved, Matth:</hi> 10.22: <hi>ſhall have the crowne of life, Rev:</hi> 2.11: <hi>When Chriſt ſhall appeare, they ſhall have confidence, and not be aſhamed before him at his comming,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.28: And they may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure themſelves, that <hi>there is laid up for them a crowne of righteouſnes, which the righteous Iudge will give unto them at that day,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.8.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which is the laſt action, whereby Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans may aſſure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:16967:135"/>of ſalvation?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>proving,</hi> and trying, approving and warranting of our Chriſtian vertues and graces: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5: For by the proofe of them, namely <hi>works of faith, labour of loue, and patience of hope,</hi> by theſe effectes S. <hi>Paule</hi> knew that the <hi>Theſſalonians, were elected of God,</hi> and that conſequently they ſhould be ſaved: 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. and what he knew of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by this meanes, they might alſo know of themſelves by the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may wee try
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:16967:136"/>and prove our graces, ſo as to approve of them for good?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>On this manner.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Our faith or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe of the Goſpell is good, when in our judge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment we do not joyne the workes of the Law with faith in Chriſt for ſalvation, but <hi>ſtand fast</hi> in this beleefe, <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.2. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15.1, 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.5. to 24.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Our repentance is good, when wee are ſorry for ſinne, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as it is dangerous to our ſoules, but as it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends God by breaking his Law, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 51.4: and
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:16967:136"/>when being rooted in the heart, it ſhewes it ſelfe in the actions of the life, by leaving for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſinne, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our lives, 1 <hi>Sam:</hi> 7.3. <hi>Matth:</hi> 3.8. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Our faith or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe in Chriſt is good, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it <hi>works in us by love</hi> to God and our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.6: and is ſhewed by <hi>good workes, Tit:</hi> 3.8. <hi>Iam:</hi> 2.18: and when it ſtirres us up to ſincere obedience to Gods commandements <hi>Hebr:</hi> 11.8.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Our feare of God is right, when we feare
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:16967:137"/>him as much for his mercy as for his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 130.2: and feare more to ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, than to be puniſhed by him, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 4.4. <hi>Gen:</hi> 39.9.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Our love of God is good, when it ſtirres us up to <hi>keepe his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, Iohn</hi> 14.15.23: when wee love him for thoſe excellent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of wiſedome and goodneſſe that are in him, as well as for the benefits that come from him; and when it ſtirres us up to <hi>hate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill</hi> and ſinne, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 97.9, 10.</p>
               <pb n="255" facs="tcp:16967:137"/>
               <p n="6">6. Our hope in God, namely, for the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to eternall life, and for Chriſts ſecond comming, is right; when being grounded on the <hi>Scriptures, Rom:</hi> 15.4, wee comfort our ſelves in our afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with it, 1 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 4.13.18: when wee pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently waite Gods lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for the obtaining of things promiſed, 1 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 1.3. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.23: and when it <hi>puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies our hearts,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.3: and makes us <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny all ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts,</hi> and <hi>to live
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:16967:138"/>righteouſly and godlily, and ſoberly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world, Titus</hi> 2.12, 13.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Good Sir, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly acknowledge my ſelfe beholden to you, for your care over me, and paines with mee; I hope I ſhall never forget it; but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſhew my ſelfe thankefull. The Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite your labour of love to me in private, by a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bleſsing upon your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery in publike; and by prolonging your life, health and ſtrength, for Gods glorie, and the good of his Church in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:16967:138"/>Christ. The Lord bee with you (Sir) and with your studies.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16967:139"/>
            <pb n="259" facs="tcp:16967:139"/>
            <head>A PRAYER <hi>FOR GRACE, TO Seeke to ſerve God, and bee ſaved.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MOſt glorious Lord God, and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father,
<note place="margin">Reu: 4, 11</note> who art <hi>worthy of all honour</hi> and ſervice,
<note place="margin">Iam: 4, 12</note> and who art <hi>able to ſave and deſtroy;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk: 17, 10</note> Thy <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſervant, unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of ſalvation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 13 46</note> doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to humble himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee; freely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging, that howſoever I am convinced in my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:16967:140"/>that nothing in this world doth ſo neerely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne me to looke unto, as thy ſervice, and mine owne ſalvation; yet my heart tells and ſmites me, that I have minded nothing leſſe then theſe, and that I have with much greedineſſe ſought after health and wealth, worldly pleaſures and treaſures, (which only belong to the body &amp; this preſent life) as if they only were worth my ſeeking, and were more able to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford me true content, than thy ſervice, and my ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt brought me into the world, and made me a member of thy Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, (chiefly) for to get grace into my heart,
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:16967:140"/>that I might ſerve thee, and live in thy feare; and alſo to get peace into my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that I might dye in thy favour, and be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſaved;
<note place="margin">2 Cor: 6; 2</note> for <hi>now is the accepted time, now is the day of ſalvation:</hi> But I have neglected the prerogative of <hi>thy ſervice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom: 9, 2</note>
               <note place="margin">Hebr: 2, 4</note> and <hi>ſo great ſalvation;</hi> and have ſpent my precious time and thoughts, in the purſuite of carthly things, which I ſhould have counted but as <hi>loſſe and dung,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil: 3, 8</note> in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>winning Chriſt,</hi> and with him ſalvation: as if I had beene borne to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end, but to ſerve the world, ſinne and Satan, and to <hi>make proviſion f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom: 13, 14</note> 
               <hi>to fulfill the luſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="262" facs="tcp:16967:141"/>
            <p>O Lord God, when I call to minde and conſider my vanity and folly, yea ungracious wickedneſſe in <hi>trampling under my feete</hi> ſuch precious pearles as are thy ſervice,
<note place="margin">Hebr: 10, 29</note> and my ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; I am confounded in my ſelfe, wondcring at thy patiencc, that couldſt ſo long endure ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull wretch to live in thy Church; yea I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and <hi>blush to lift up my face to thee, becauſe this mine iniquity is increaſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 9, 6</note> 
               <hi>and my wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe is growne up unto heaven,</hi> crying for venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon ſuch contempt of thy grace,
<note place="margin">Iohn 3, 19</note> it being <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to love darkneſſe more than light,</hi> earth more than heaven, and the world
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:16967:141"/>more than thee, or mine owne ſoule.</p>
            <p>But thy <hi>mercy</hi> (O Lord God) <hi>is over all thy workes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal: 145, 9 138, 8.</note> and <hi>endures for ever:</hi> It is as great as thy Majeſty, and thy goodneſſe is as much as thy greatneſſe, and the blood of Ieſus Chriſt is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to <hi>wash mee</hi> ſo cleane <hi>from my ſinnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel: 1, 5</note> that I ſhall be holy,
<note place="margin">Eph: 5, 27</note> and <hi>without ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh before thee:</hi> therefore <hi>there is hope in Iſrael con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this thing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 10, 2</note> And therefore upon the bended knees of my heavy laden ſoule, I moſt humbly cry thee mercy, (moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Father) for this and all other my ſinnes originall and actuall, committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law and the Goſpell: and with all the
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:16967:142"/>powers of my ſoule moſt earneſtly beſeech thee <hi>for the Lords ſake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan: 9, 17 Iſay 53, 11 Acts 3, 14. Mat: 3, 17</note> 
               <hi>thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſervant, the holy One, and the juſt, in whom thou art well pleaſed,</hi> to forgive me, to be reconciled unto me; and to <hi>ſhed thy love into my heart by thy holy Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom: 5, 5</note> which may <hi>beare witneſſe to my Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">&amp;c. 8, 16.</note> 
               <hi>that I am thy Childe,</hi> beloved in thy <hi>holy Childe Ieſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 4, 27</note> Let thy mercy move thee to looke upon his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to juſtify me, when thy juſtice would make thee looke upon my ſinnes to condemne me: Accept of him for my <hi>ſurety,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 7.22</note> and of the price of his blood for my ranſome.
<note place="margin">1 Pet: 1, 23</note> Thou haſt ſaid (O bleſſed God) that <hi>whoſoever comes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat: 11, 28</note> 
               <hi>unto thy
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:16967:142"/>Sonne Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh: 6, 35.</note> 
               <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves in him,</hi> with an <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie laden ſoule,</hi> wearie of their former wickedneſſe, thou wilt eaſe and forgive them.
<note place="margin">1 Iohn 1: 9</note> Oh <hi>be juſt and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> to make good this promiſe unto me, to eaſe and to ſave me. I deſire to honour thy infinite mercy, and thy Sonnes unvaluable merits, by ſeeking to them onely, and truſting in them alone for ſalvation. O be thou pleaſed alſo to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie them upon me; for I have as much need of them as any,
<note place="margin">1 Tim: 1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5</note> (being <hi>the chiefe of ſinners</hi>) and the ſaving ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of them ſhall be mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified in the cure of my ſoule, as well as of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>It hath pleaſed thee (hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:16967:143"/>Father) to give unto me (in ſome meaſure) a ſight and ſenſe of my ſins, (par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly) of my neglect and contempt of thy ſervice, and my ſalvation: Oh be pleaſed (I beſeech thee) yet more and more to diſcover unto me the folly and foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this and all my ſinnes, that my heart may be ſo broken with godly remorſe and ſorrow for them, that I may leave them, and live no longer in them; but cleave unto thee, to ſerve thee in new obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for <hi>what will it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit</hi> me <hi>to winne the whole world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.26</note> 
               <hi>and to loſe</hi> thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and <hi>mine owne ſoule?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh,
<note place="margin">1 Pet: 4.3.</note> it is <hi>enough,</hi> and too much, that I have already ſpent ſo much time of my
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:16967:143"/>life paſt in worldly vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and I cannot tell how little I have to ſpend here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; and therefore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee give me conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to <hi>redeeme</hi> it,
<note place="margin">Eph: 5.16.</note> and to ſpend the remainder in thy ſervice, and in the aſſuring to my ſelfe <hi>my calling,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet: 1.10 Phil: 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and ſalvation;</hi> that I may yet at length (before it be too late) <hi>ſeeke thy kingdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat: 6.33.</note> 
               <hi>and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk: 13.24 Hebr: 4.11. Iohn 6.27</note> 
               <hi>ſtrive to enter into thy ſtrait gate:</hi> and <hi>labour to enter into that reſt:</hi> and <hi>for the meate that endures to life eternall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beſeech thee enlighten my minde more and more with the knowledge of thoſe chiefe points of thy ſervice, and my ſalvation, which doe moſt neerely
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:16967:144"/>concerne me, and which are revealed in thy holy word: Inflame my heart with the love of them, that I may ſet it upon them; and quicken up my conſcience to endeavour (in the uſe of all holy meanes afforded for this end) to practiſe thy ſervice in ſuch a manner and meaſure of ſinceritie, and conſtancy, that in the end I may attaine the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my ſoule.</p>
            <p>For this end I moſt humbly beſeech thee to give me power, wholly to renounce the ſervice of ſin, Satan, and the world, that I may give my ſelfe to thy ſervice; to moderate my deſires to earthly things, <hi>(uſing the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor: 7, 31 Col: 3, 1.</note> 
               <hi>as not abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it)</hi> that I may <hi>ſet my
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:16967:144"/>affections on things above;</hi> becauſe I ſee <hi>I cannot ſerve God and Mammon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat 6.24.</note> Yet give me (I pray thee) a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie of Neceſſaries for this life, without which I cannot well ſerve thee in my place, and with my charge;
<note place="margin">1 Tim 6, 8. Prov 30.8.</note> even <hi>foode and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrell convenient;</hi> and a ſanctified uſe of them; or a holy want of them, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing content, that I enjoy thee as my portion, though I had nothing elſe beſides.</p>
            <p>Good Lord, (I beſeech thee) ſtrengthen my faith in Chriſt daily, and renew my repentance for my dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinnes. Confirme my hope of a joyfull reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to eternall life; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe my patience under all afflictions, learning dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:16967:145"/>to <hi>take up my Croſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 9.23</note> 
               <hi>and to follow Chriſt.</hi> Make me watchfull over my <hi>deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier: 17.10. Prov: 4.</note> 
               <hi>to keepe it with all diligence,</hi> that it let not ſin either in or out; and give me wiſedome to <hi>cut</hi> from the ſenſes and members of my bodie,
<note place="margin">Mat: 5, 29</note> all occaſions and opportunities of doing ill.</p>
            <p>Worke in me conſcience to be diligent and faithfull in my place and calling wherein I live, to doe all the duties thereof as <hi>unto thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col: 3, 22 Rom: 14, 12 Deutr. 32, 29 Pſal: 90, 12</note> to whom <hi>I muſt give an accompt.</hi> And for that end give me <hi>wiſedome to conſider my latter end, to number my dayes;</hi> and to remember that one day, (I know not how ſoone) I muſt die,
<note place="margin">Eccle: 11, 9</note> and come to judgement.</p>
            <pb n="271" facs="tcp:16967:145"/>
            <p>Remember in mercy (O heavenly Father I beſeech thee) with me, thy whole Church, to ſettle peace and the Goſpell therein. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue thy bleſſings of thy pure worſhip, and ſafety to our Land, and the other Kingdomes; and for that end governe all our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, (ſpecially our Soveraigne Lord King CHARLES, and our Royall Queene MARY) with that wiſedome of thy Spirit,
<note place="margin">Pſal: 111, 10 2 Tim: 3.15</note> the <hi>beginning where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is thy feare,</hi> and the end their owne <hi>ſalvation.</hi> Be comfortable (oh Father of mercie) to all thy children in affliction; eaſe the pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, cure the diſeaſed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the diſtreſſed, viſit the ſicke, and either <hi>deliver Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:16967:146"/>out of her troubles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 25, 22</note> or ſanctifie their ſeverall croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to their humiliation and converſion, conſolation and ſalvation in Ieſus Chriſt. Forget not to bleſſe my kindred, allies and friends, with a long, holy and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous life (if it be thy will) in this world, with a comfortable <hi>departure in peace</hi> out of the ſame,
<note place="margin">Luke 2, 29</note> and with an eternall and happy life in the world to come: and for that end make them deare unto thee in Ieſus Chriſt, and by thy holy Spirit, as they are neare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me in any bond of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or grace, of law or love, and of neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood or friendſhip.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, oh heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according to my
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:16967:146"/>bounden dutie I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> give thee thankes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thy mercies beſtowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> me, mine, and all thine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> things temporall, ſpiritual and eternall; for this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life, and a better that is to come, upon our bodies and ſoules. Of them all I acknowledge thee the bountifull giver and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer; and of them all I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my ſelfe to be a moſt unworthy receiver, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my ſinnes, (ſpecially my great unthank fulneſſe:) Notwithſtanding I doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire unfeignedly, and (by thy grace) will earneſtly endeavour, that thou maiſt have more ſincere and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſervice, with and for all the good benefits which I have received from thee.
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:16967:147"/>And therefore <hi>unto the King immortall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim: 1, 17</note> 
               <hi>inviſible, and onely wiſe God,</hi> and mercifull Father, be given with all the parts and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of my ſoule and body, in Ieſus Chriſt, by the holy Spirit, all glory and thanks, with obedience &amp; ſervice, from this preſent time, and from henceforth for evermore: <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:16967:147"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>ATtributes of God what they be. Pag.</hi> 19</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Greatneſſe. Pag.</hi> 20</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The duties belonging to them. Pag.</hi> 28</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Goodneſſe. Pag.</hi> 24</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties to them. Pag.</hi> 29</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Almightineſſe of God. Pag.</hi> 23</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Adoption. Pag.</hi> 138</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties of Chriſtians in reſpect of Baptiſme. Pag.</hi> 59</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties of Christians to their bodies. Pag.</hi> 87</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:16967:148"/>
            <list>
               <head>C.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties belonging to our Chriſtian Calling. Pag.</hi> 88</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Commandements of the word, and duties to them. Pag.</hi> 48.49</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The two chiefe duties of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Pag.</hi> 5</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Eternity of God. Pag.</hi> 21</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Holy Exerciſes. Pag.</hi> 34</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties before wee come to them, Pag.</hi> 36</item>
               <item>2. <hi>At the time of them. Pag.</hi> 37</item>
               <item>3. <hi>After them. Pag.</hi> 38</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Examples of the word. Pag.</hi> 53</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties in reſpect of them. Pag.</hi> 54</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Faith. Pag.</hi> 29</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:16967:148"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Faculties in God. Pag.</hi> 20</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>What GOD is. Pag.</hi> 19</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What generall duties belong to him, Pag.</hi> 17</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What ſpeciall duties. Pag.</hi> 18</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How wee may bee moved to ſeeke grace. Pag.</hi> 114</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To uſe grace. Pag.</hi> 115</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The regenerate fall not from grace. Pag.</hi> 181</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Holineſſe of God. Pag.</hi> 24</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What the hearing of the word is, Pag.</hi> 44</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties in reſpect of it. Pag.</hi> 45</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Immenſity of God. Pag.</hi> 22</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:16967:149"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Infiniteneſſe of GOD. Pag.</hi> 21</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iuſtice of GOD. Pag.</hi> 25</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iustification. Pag.</hi> 137</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>What things we muſt know of God. Pag.</hi> 17</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The love of GOD to us, Pag.</hi> 26</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Our love to GOD.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To our Neighbour.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Mercy of GOD. Pag.</hi> 25</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties to our Neighbour.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>1. <hi>Generall. Pag.</hi> 81</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Speciall. Pag.</hi> 82</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Common to all.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Peculiar to ſome. Pag.</hi> 83</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:16967:149"/>
            <list>
               <head>O.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>What GODS holy Ordinances are. Pag.</hi> 31</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of what kindes they are. Pag.</hi> 32</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties belonging to them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties to our ſelves. Pag.</hi> 86</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Promiſes of the word.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What they be. Pag.</hi> 50</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties to them. Pag.</hi> 51</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Praying to GOD, what it is. Pag.</hi> 61</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties about it. Pag.</hi> 62</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Praiſing GOD, what it is. Pag.</hi> 67</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties about it. Pag.</hi> 68</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Preſervation of the holy Spirit. Pag.</hi> 181</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Perfections in GOD. Pag.</hi> 19</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Reſurrection proved. Pag.</hi> 144</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:16967:150"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>That it is a bleſsing to the faithfull. Pag.</hi> 148</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The difference betwixt the raiſing of the godly and wicked. Pag.</hi> 153</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Reconciliation with God. Pag.</hi> 137</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Regeneration of the Spirit. Pag.</hi> 174</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whereunto. Pag.</hi> 176</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whereby. Pag.</hi> 180</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Christians must ſeeke to be ſaved. Pag.</hi> 124</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why. Pag.</hi> 125</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>By what meanes. Pag.</hi> 132</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What ſalvation is. Pag.</hi> 133</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The degrees of it:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In this life. Pag.</hi> 137</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>At the end of it, Pag.</hi> 139</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>At the end of the world. Pag.</hi> 143</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The meanes to effect ſalvation. Pag.</hi> 159</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Actions of GOD the Father. Pag.</hi> 160</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:16967:150"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Sonne. Pag.</hi> 161</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The holy Ghoſt. Pag.</hi> 174</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seeking to be affected with ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Pag.</hi> 202</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The poſsibility of ſalvation. Pag.</hi> 203</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The neceſsity of it. Pag.</hi> 205</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Excellency of it. Pag.</hi> 207</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Certainty of it. Pag.</hi> 209</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seeking to get ſalvation. Pag.</hi> 218</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Actions of men that prepare them to ſalvation. Pag.</hi> 223</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To claime and receive it. Pag.</hi> 226</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To aſſure it. Pag.</hi> 231</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>That we must ſerve. Pag.</hi> 8</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why we muſt. Pag.</hi> 9</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The manner how to ſeeke to ſerve GOD. Pag.</hi> 11</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The meaſure. Pag.</hi> 12</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The workes of them that ſeeke to ſerve GOD. Pag.</hi> 13</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What GODS ſervice is. Pag.</hi> 15</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:16967:151"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why wee muſt ſeeke to ſerve GOD while we live. Pag.</hi> 14</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Service to GOD immediately in reſpect of himſelfe. Pag.</hi> 17</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties to our ſoules. Pag.</hi> 87</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seeking to be affected with his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice Pag.</hi> 94</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Neceſsity of it. Pag.</hi> 96</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Excellency. Pag.</hi> 97</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Equity. Pag.</hi> 98</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Reward. Pag.</hi> 99</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties in reſpect of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Pag.</hi> 32</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seeking to practiſe GODS ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Pag.</hi> 101</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The manner of practiſe. Pag.</hi> 102</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meaſure. Pag.</hi> 104</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>End, why. Pag.</hi> 110</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meanes, whereby. Pag.</hi> 112</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How wee may ſeeke grace to ſerve GOD. Pag.</hi> 114</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:16967:151"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Simpleneſſe of GOD. Pag.</hi> 21</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties about receiving the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Pag.</hi> 55</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Threatnings of GOD, what they be. Pag.</hi> 52</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties about them. Pag.</hi> 53</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vertues in GOD. Pag.</hi> 24</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Wiſedome of GOD. Pag.</hi> 22</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What it is to worſhip GOD. Pag.</hi> 39</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Difference betwixt ſervice and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Pag.</hi> 40</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The workes sf GOD. Pag.</hi> 72</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duties about them. Pag.</hi> 73</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>GODS workes of mercy. Pag.</hi> 74</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iuſtice. Pag.</hi> 75</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="faults">
            <pb facs="tcp:16967:152"/>
            <head>Faults eſcaped.</head>
            <p>Page 10. line 2. after <hi>them,</hi> reade <hi>that ſeeke him.</hi> p. 30 in the margent; for <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately</hi> r. mediately; and put out <hi>as his ordinances.</hi> p. 52. l. 13. for <hi>and</hi> r. or. p. 97. l. 1. for <hi>greater</hi> r. great. p. 114. l. 5. for <hi>remedy</hi> r. reward thereof. p. 116. l. laſt; after <hi>unto you,</hi> r. for inſtruction. p. 131. l. 4. after <hi>dye</hi> r. and not till then. p. 135. l. 8. after <hi>is</hi> r. alſo. p. 187. l. 18. after <hi>end</hi> r. through faith. p: 220: l: 19: for <hi>by faith</hi> r. by his faith. p: 221: l: laſt, for <hi>their</hi> r. them. p: 232: l: 9: for <hi>aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi> r. aſſuring. p: 247: l: 11. put out <hi>that.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16967:152"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
